Where do people go? If you're moved on from everywhere, there is
nowhere to be. Death from homelessness.
Caitlin died at 47, ill, rundown, and fatigued after
having to sleep outside in Christchurch in late autumn
2025 from two respiratory infections,
including the common cold because of her lifelong
immunosuppression to prevent her kidney transplant rejecting.
Caitlin's previous hospital renal specialist concluded in his report I
provided the coroner, "With suitable and stable housing, Caitlin should
have had many years of life ahead of her with a functioning
transplant."
Her death was entirely preventable, but inevitable given the
failures of those with a duty of care,
MSD, Ministry of Social Development, Public Trust,
the health system, and New Zealand Police.
Caitlin was brave, ethical, articulate, and persevering.
She stood up for herself.
People found that difficult.
Caitlin lived in miserable, unhealthy, and unsafe conditions, sleeping in
parks until moved on or abused by neighbors, in derelict
houses, or taken in by people who professed to help her but preyed on
her.
She was abused, attacked, assaulted, and stolen from
repeatedly. My daughter survived less than two years
homeless, dying at half the age of both her grandmothers.
Homeless people die 30 years early.
Caitlin wrote that the previous year hospital told her that if she
continued to live outdoors in winter, she would not survive to spring.
Family and others slept in that winter.
As recent New Zealand research finds, homeless people die 30 years
earlier than the rest of us with a roof over our heads.
And to quote from that report, "Premature mortality results
from a complex combination of medical conditions, often related
to severe and chronic comorbidities, and the consequences of
social exclusion shaped by homelessness." That is
marginalization and stigma, loneliness,
violence, and adverse living conditions.
That's what the move on orders will do even more.
MSD refused Caitlin housing.
Caitlin was not provided a permanent home, despite MSD
assessing her as A20, the top of the social housing wait list,
nor did MSD provide her with emergency housing for more than a year.
I am now walking in Caitlin's shoes, experiencing the same rejection and
runaround, showing how difficult it is to navigate a fragmented,
unresponsive, and unaccountable system, then and
now. Caitlin had no chance. Now we know that MSD
has incentives for managers and staff to turn down emergency
housing, meeting government targets set in
2024 five years early.
Even more shockingly, I found out that MSD does not have to
consider whether declining emergency housing would,
in quotes, "Increase or create any risk to the welfare
or life of the applicant."
Public Trust then rejected her GP certification in February
2025 that Caitlin was at serious and imminent risk of
death to enable her to withdraw her $48,000
KiwiSaver to be safely housed and cared for without
taking any medical advice at all.
She was found dead three months later after having to sleep outside in late
autumn.
Move on orders push homeless people to the margins away from
support.
Move on orders risk pushing people further away from housing,
outreach support services, trusted relationships, vital health
services, and basic public amenities such as showers,
toilets, and lockers.
Caitlin's GP and pharmacy were in central Christchurch, as was WINZ, the
food bank, and other support services, and the library where she spent her days
in a warm, safe environment with free Wi-Fi.
Police did not protect Caitlin as she expected, instead arresting her,
including during welfare checks.
That is, Caitlin was already criminalized,
homeless, never having been in trouble with police before.
Police did not refer her to housing as government states is the police role
when issuing move on orders. Police themselves oppose this.
Police did not even ensure she was safe when assisting her to leave yet another
unsuitable place with a 24 hours safety order the
weekend before she was found dead in the same flat she had
returned on her own solely to collect her warm gear, it being
cold.
Instead of moving homeless people to the margins, police need to be required to
refer rough sleepers to a home, together with connecting them with the help
and other support they need.
Moving on homelessness. As the Auditor-General recommends in his
March
2026 report, Supporting People in Immediate
Housing Need, a joined up government response is essential to make real
progress in reducing the extent of homelessness and unstable housing.
The proposed move on orders do the opposite.
A duty to assist is needed instead.
We need an integrated approach, listening to those who know,
across party and across government.
To end,
my beautiful daughter.
To end, Caitlin was my beautiful daughter.
Caitlin could be your daughter.
She could be your sister,
your friend, your cousin, your aunt.
This could happen to any of us.
Housing is a human right: decent, warm,
affordable, secure housing.
With a home, everything else can be sorted as the housing first approach
Thank you.
Since my 2nd of July written submission,
I have attached,
and this is my supplementary submission,
three pieces that came out last week.
"Honoring Caitlin, Calling for Change" by the Coalition to End Women's
Homelessness
last Thursday.
"Christchurch is my home," my tomb, sorry.
Freudian slip. "Christchurch is my tomb,"
not my home. "From homelessness to helplessness," by Jean
Edwards, Radio New Zealand, 16th of July.
And, "Before her death, Caitlin McDonald needed a home and wraparound care,
not rejection," again by Jean of Radio New Zealand
on the 17th of July.
So, if you have any questions, I'd be very happy to try and answer them.
Thank you, Wendy. We have one question from Camilla Palmer.
Thank you so much for your heartfelt submission, Wendy.
And first of all, can I say on behalf of the committee, we're so sorry for the loss
of Caitlin, and also commend you for your courage in honoring
her today at the select committee.
Thank you.
My question for you is, what is the one thing that you would like to see
Parliament do for people like Caitlin?
That's a good question.
It's that joined up, integrated approach.
In terms of the move on orders, which I've focused on today,
I would like them not to go ahead. And
I could be daring and invite anybody, there's
three parties in the coalition government.
There's other parties.
They shouldn't go ahead because
for poorally traumatized people, it really would be the end.
And
they need care, and I think it's time this country
has that integrated approach, the sustainable approach,
and put all the things that are needed together.
And it's not just for the extreme end of homelessness, it's actually to make
sure everybody,
the generation below me and below that, cannot
afford a home. Whereas in my day, we were helped by
government into a home.
And our home ownership rates have gone down a lot.
But also, of course, renting has to be right.
My daughter was evicted once.
Mm.
So I'd like to see
that integrated approach across party and across government,
looking at all the facets for everyone.
Because
without housing, and my daughter died because of that,
completely preventable but inevitable.
So please think of the people on the streets.
I live in Newtown, Wellington.
I've seen that, and I knew nothing about homelessness when this happened to
Caitlin, and I was pretty useless.
I'm sorry, and I apologize to my daughter.
But she was a proud person who wanted to do it, who had to be in control of
her life because of the risks to her health.
She almost died of sepsis in 2019. So she's
a very capable person.
So I'm sorry, but I would like everybody to work together.
I don't have instant solutions, but I think this is a problem that's been coming
across governments of whatever complexion for a very long
time,
and we've got to ... We're New Zealand. We're a lovely, beautiful country.
Thank you.
Thank you, Wendy. And thank you very much for-
Thank you
... being here with us today, and your submission as well-
And thank you for having me
... on behalf of Caitlin, too.
That was here at three when I first worked in Parliament in
1980.
Thank you.
She probably toddled around the corridors here.
Thank you so much.
Thanks, Wendy.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Okay. Our next submission is going to be on Zoom, and it's going to be from Alison.
Hey, Alison.
Hello. Hiya.
Thank you very ... We're here. Thank you very much for joining us this afternoon.
We've read your submission. We've got you down for five minutes.
Yep.
If you can just leave a little bit of time at the end for any questions members
might have.
Sure.
I've got some notes. I'll refer to those briefly, but I'll be as
rapid as I can. I understand that
this process is being live streamed, and that
previous hearings are also available.
That's right.
Make them widely available. I just want to note that in the absence
of anyone who is signing, or the provision of a New Zealand Sign Language
interpreter, these are inaccessible to anyone whose
first lang-
or preferred language is New Zealand Sign Language.
So I find that disappointing, but unsurprising.
I just want to note that.
In summary, my submission said that the proposed legislation
is cruel and unnecessary, and I'll just very briefly speak to that.
It's cruel because it targets and punishes homeless and other
vulnerable people. Does nothing to support them.
And it's unnecessary because there is current legislation that already addresses
antisocial and difficult behaviors.
What it does is it creates new crime out of behaviors that
I would see, and many others would see, as not serious issues.
I'd note that kind of two groups opposing this
legislation.
Organizations that are involved, and individuals such as the previous
speaker, who have a direct involvement and concern for
people who are homeless and otherwise vulnerable.
Churches, for example. The Police Association
I'm not going to repeat any of their advice, but I strongly urge the committee to
consider and follow their advice.
They are experts and knowledgeable in this area.
The other group that I see opposed to this legislation is
individuals like me who don't have a direct involvement, but are
concerned about the intent and the effects of this legislation.
I want the committee to know that ordinary Zealanders are opposed.
You should note and respond to those concerns constructively and
positively.
Finally, I want to offer a challenge to the committee, in fact,
to all MPs really.
If you are concerned about the wellbeing of people who are homeless and
similarly vulnerable, and you all should be, I challenge you
to do something.
I'm not in paid employment. I donate material goods,
time, effort, and money, principally through knitting.
I knit scarves and hats that are distributed to people in need
in Auckland every winter. I've got one on the go at the moment.
Yeah.
You don't have to knit,
although you could. We're all in a position to donate money,
obviously, and I hope you do. But I do challenge you
to donate time and effort as well to make a difference.
Thank you. That's my speech.
Fantastic. Thanks, Allison. We've got a question here from Dan Roseborne.
Thanks for that submission, Allison.
Now, if the government's goal is to reduce rough sleeping and
improve public safety, what approaches do you think would
be more effective than move on orders?
Well, I think move on orders have no impact or are not
designed even to help that.
But again, I'd repeat what I said earlier, which is
follow the advice of organizations that know what they're
doing and already work with homeless and other vulnerable people.
And they are united, I think, in saying that move on orders
are not the way to resolve problems
for people who are homeless or are similarly vulnerable.
Fantastic. Thank you, Allison. We really appreciate both your written and your
oral submission to us today, this afternoon. So thanks for joining us.
Thank you.
Right. Next, we have Madison, who's going to be joining us in person.
Thanks, Madison. You've obviously heard the last couple of submitters.
You've got five minutes. We've read your submission.
But please do leave a little bit of time for questions. Over to you.
Kia ora, everyone. My name's Madison, and I'm a solicitor.
And in my final year of uni, I did an entire law honors dissertation
on the law's impact with homeless people.
That's what I'm relying on today
in my personal capacity. So in my recent submissions, I did six recommendations.
Today, I'm going to be talking about three of them.
The very first one is the bill's stated purpose is to stop
disorderly, threatening, and intimidating behavior.
Rough sleeping and begging are not examples of that, and the bill
doesn't fill a genuine legislative gap.
On a common sense understanding, those behaviors are survival
behaviors carried out in public because the person has nowhere else
to go. And secondly, because the city center is generally safer
with more police and more traffic than other areas of the city.
Section 3 and 5A of the Summary Offences Act already
cover threatening, disorderly, and obstructive behavior.
So do council bylaws right across the country.
If that is the stated purpose of this bill, then it is really doing a
completely unrelated thing. It is stopping the presence of homeless
people in the city. Homeless people are not disorder.
You can see that most clearly in the specific bill's carve outs.
Rough sleeping excludes freedom camping.
Begging excludes charity collectors.
If you're collecting on behalf of a charity, that's fine.
But if you're a homeless person trying to collect your money for dinner, that's not
okay. Just in plain terms, you can be poor,
vulnerable, and homeless, but do it somewhere else.
Just to reiterate, begging and rough sleeping are not disorder.
They are people trying to survive.
I ask the committee to remove from Section 8A of the bill, sub clause
E and F.
The second is the age threshold. Under this bill, a 14-year-old can
be given a move on order for rough sleeping or begging.
A 14-year-old sleeping rough is a child in crisis,
which requires child protection, emergency housing, and social
work. It does not require a fine. Once a child is in the
justice system, it is very hard to get them back out.
The bill in its current form is helping to funnel homeless children
into the criminal justice system.
They're being criminalized for normal behavior and then being fined an
amount that they cannot pay, which may lead to imprisonment.
Which imprisonment on its own has a lifetime effects of
including discriminating children for their status before they've even had a real
chance of working or finding a home that an
adult should be providing to them.
New Zealanders want homeless people, including children, to
be housed, not moved on.
I ask the committee to raise the minimum age to 18 at the minimum.
The third is the cost. A move on fine can run to $2,000.
Someone with no income simply cannot pay that.
Non-payment becomes a warrant, which becomes court time and can end in
imprisonment. We all know that imprisonment costs
about $50,000 a person per year in taxpayer dollars.
That's not an effective use of public money, and no cost assessment of
this bill's enforcement provisions has been published.
I'd ask that one is before this bill goes any further.
So my submission is really narrow.
You need to be removing rough sleeping and begging as grounds for a move on order.
And secondly The minimum age should be raised to 18 at the
least. Once those provisions are removed, it becomes illogical to have
this bill in place at all. We've already got Summary Offences Act,
which covers disorderly and offensive behavior.
Welcome any questions.
Thank you, Madison. We've got a question from Camilla Belich.
Thanks for your submission, and amazing that you've done research in this area.
It's a really well-written submission. I'm really put.
I just had a question around the age threshold, which I agree
with you on that point. But we've had some people come to the committee and say,
"Well, the criminal age of responsibility is 14." Can you
just maybe expand a bit on what you've put in your written submission around-
Yeah
...
kind of the practicalities of how
removing that age from 14 to 18 would
work?
Yeah.
The main reason why I've made the age 18 is because if you've got
a child who's homeless, any age under 18
is you're really expecting a parent to be there and helping them get housed.
That's evidently not happening if they're age 14 to 18.
So at minimum, we should be raising it to 18, just so
that we're putting those people who are disadvantaged on the same position as
an ordinary New Zealander who's got parents who are helping them get housed.
There's so many other reasons for that, too.
It's just like-
Yeah. That's a really good point, I think, that we haven't heard before as well,
that if they are on the street, then effectively that's an indication that there
either isn't a parent involved or that that-
Yeah
... parental responsibility is not being exercised, I think.
Yeah.
Anything else?
Thank you, Madison. That's the end of our time with you, but we really appreciate
your hard work and your submission today.
Thank you.
Thanks. Thank you very much. Our next submitter is Kyle.
Hey, Kyle. Thank you for joining us this afternoon.
We've read your written submission, and we've got you down for five minutes.
Over to you.
Thank you. Tēnā koutou katoa. As you've read in my submission, my name is Kyle
Sumval, and I speak to you today to strongly oppose this move on a dispell.
I really feel it is the most disgusting and depraved thing those of you in the
coalition have produced. And I thank the members of this committee who are going to
be willing to fight against it during this process.
I live, work, and study in the beautiful Te Whanganui-a-Tara, Wellington.
Unlike some of yourselves who get around in Ubers and private cars, I actually walk
and bus around this city, so I come into daily contact with the people who are
going to be affected by this bill. These are people you have abandoned,
mischaracterized, disrespected, and who you finally seek to subject to the
further indignity and violence of harassment, relocation, and
imprisonment.
The other day, I spoke to a man who was committing what under this bill would be
the crime of begging.
I'd given him $20, and he asked if I was a Christian.
I said that I wasn't, and he said that I must just be a person with heart.
He said the world was broken, and I agreed.
I remembered seeing this guy on the night of the terrible floods in Wellington
earlier this year.
My friends had lost their home and many of their precious belongings in this flood.
And as this news was coming to me, I sat horrified on their behalf.
But also, as a citizen of Wellington, I was also increasingly thinking about what
would be happening to all the people who had less, those who slept in the street.
What were you thinking about on that day,
you who are paid to represent all of us in Aotearoa?
What would you do if you saw this guy sitting in soaking wet clothes in
the corner of a cold supermarket lobby?
How would you feel if it was you sitting there?
Are you capable of such a basic empathetic response?
Or would you identify with the people who would turn up their nose at him, who
were scared of him?
Are you identifying with the business owners who want to get rid of these
people, who don't actually care what happens to them as long as they're out of
their sight?
Under this bill,
I guess you would call the cops. Shame on you.
If you can excuse and work alongside perpetrators of violence
yourselves, perpetrators who haven't had a day of adversity in their lives,
perhaps you could excuse people for talking aloud to themselves, for
sleeping on the street, for begging, for lashing out, for
scaring people when they're experiencing the most difficult conditions to
be found in this country under reprehensible economic
management. Our economy doesn't function for
the sake of your rich friends. It's for all of us.
If there are people who can't sleep in their own safe and warm homes, it is
truly broken.
Why should I, simply as a human with a heart, feel more
responsibility towards the homeless and vulnerable than you?
I guess because I imagine my role in my community as caring
for, loving, and protecting others, and you think of your role as something
else entirely. Protecting legal economic exchange, I guess.
I don't want the community, the economy, or the world that this bill
imagines. I hate it, and I reject it.
If you support this bill through this process, I tell you, if you still have
one, there is so, so, so much work to be done on your heart.
Thank you. I'll take questions.
Thank you, Kyle. We have a question from Dan Rosewarne.
Thanks, Kyle. I appreciate that submission.
I found this passage in your submission particularly interesting.
"Conversation, donation, and other interaction with homeless and
otherwise vulnerable people reminds me that I'm part of a community."
Your submission talks about homelessness as something that affects the whole
community rather than something that sits outside of it.
And my question is, how do you think legislation like this changes
the way the public sees people experiencing homelessness?
It's just horrific because you think that if you feel a negative response when you
see a homeless person, what that negative response really is, is
guilt and shame and sadness. It should be sadness and empathy.
And if this bill passes, what it's going to be is fear.
It's going to be blaming that person for what's happening to them, and it's wanting
to get rid of them So I think that you are twisting the basic empathetic
responses of human beings in their communities, and you're telling them to call the
cops on people that they should be reaching out to help and protect.
Thank you.
Thank you, Carl. Thank you very much for your written submission and for joining us
this afternoon as well.
Thank you. And I really support the submissions we had before as well, and that
we're here following.
Fantastic.
Thank you.
Thank you very much. All right, our next submitter is the New Zealand Law Society,
Nicola and Debra, and they're going to be joining us on Zoom.
Sorry, problem with mute.
My name's Debbie Wilson, and I'm a member of the Criminal Law Committee of the New
Zealand Law Society, and I'm joined with Nicola Manning from the Human Rights and
Privacy Committee.
Thanks, Debbie. We've got Nicola's camera on.
We just can't see you, unfortunately.
Good afternoon.
No.
I can't get it to work either, sorry.
That's okay. Feel free to go ahead. You've got 10 minutes.
We have read your submission.
Oh, yep.
There you go.
There I am.
Please do just leave some time for questions. Over to you.
Sure. So I'm going to talk briefly about the general concerns with the bill and
then pass on to Nicola to discuss the Bill of Rights Act issues.
The Law Society has significant concerns about this bill.
We feel that it adopts a broad discretionary and coercive framework,
and we feel that it infringes on several fundamental rights.
It's therefore our recommendation that the bill not proceed, and we feel that even
if significant changes are made, the bill is going to still remain fundamentally
flawed.
Just to highlight some of our concerns.
The first is that we feel that the work undertaken by the Retail Ministry
Advisory Group is not a substitute for a full policy development process,
and it's clear from the risk impact statement that this has not happened.
More work is needed, and more voices need to be heard before this bill can be
justified.
We note that in relation to the recent Trespass Bill, the views of the Ministry
Advisory Group was not shared by other retail representatives, and
that's a real problem.
Second, we're concerned that while this bill is clearly intended to work alongside
the Trespass Specific Retail Premises and Other Matters Amendment bill,
the two are being considered separately in committee.
We feel that the only way for the committee, for Parliament, and for the public to
truly understand the combined effect of these two bills is for them to be
considered together.
Both of them suffer from the same lack of policy development,
and they allow people who engage in conduct that is undesirable but not
criminal,
to be potentially banned from large areas and denied access to essential
services. Again, it's targeting conduct that is not criminal, but it's
imposing criminal sanctions on these people without proper process.
Before I hand over to Ms. Manning, I would just like to highlight some of the
examples of the broad language that we are concerned about.
First, the bill requires only that police have a reasonable grounds to suspect that
relevant conduct has occurred. So relevant grounds to suspect.
While we recognize that this does allow for benevolence and discretion on behalf of
the police, it also risks inconsistency of application.
A standard of reasonable grounds to believe would be more appropriate and would set
a slightly higher standard.
We're also concerned that rough sleeping is an independent ground for a move on
order to be made, but it's not defined anywhere, which leaves a very broad
scope for these orders, and we feel that it should be either entirely removed
or defined clearly and narrowly. And we note that this is a view that
has been expressed by many people talking about this bill.
I'll now hand over to Ms. Manning to discuss some of the Bill of Rights Act issues
with the bill.
Thank you. Good afternoon. I do highlight that
the concerns in terms of rights
are manifold and include that the bill impinges on the
right to freedom of expression, the right to protest, freedom of
movement, the right not to be arbitrarily detained, and the right
to procedural fairness. The core submission that the Law
Society makes is that the bill ought not to proceed,
and particularly with the inclusion of begging and rough sleeping as
grounds for orders to be made. But what I wanted to just
highlight this afternoon are the safeguards that
we have suggested so that if the bill is to proceed,
those safeguards are in place to limit the
impingement on rights. And I do highlight that these
are safeguards that are in place in other jurisdictions where similar powers
of this nature have been
provided.
The first
recommendation is that police should be required to consider the
effect of issuing a move on order on the person's personal safety.
The committee has heard extensively from submitters, and I was
online when Caitlin's mother, who probably highlighted it far better than I could
in terms of access to those essential services
that a lot of people in these positions do rely on,
transportation, healthcare, education, and the like.
And that would be consistent with legislation in other jurisdictions,
including Australia.
The second is that the bill doesn't provide
clear directions about distance and time when
orders are made. So there is no direction to the police on how
far a person must move
or leave the public place specified.
This is going to give rise to confusion and inconsistencies
between what different police officers may
require. The other issue is that there's no guidance as to how
promptly an individual who's served an order must move.
And in fact, Section 8F appears to have conflicting
tests between it. It refers to both immediately as well
as within a reasonable timeframe.
And it's suggested or recommended that those
powers are
amended to clarify those matters.
The third recommendation is to avoid the risk or
to limit perhaps the risk of arbitrary detention, is a
recommended new Section 8C (1) , to
provide for an amount of time that a person being
required to provide biographical details can be
detained. We've suggested that it ought to be no longer than
15 minutes, which is consistent with the existing powers in Section
114 of the Land Transport Act. And I do highlight
particularly that in terms of those biographical details listed, some of
them may well be very difficult for a
person to provide who is being considered for
a move on order. So to allow police sort of unlimited time frames
to seek to procure that information is
undesirable in our submission.
The Section 8
, it is suggested should be amended to ensure that
or to require that any explanation
as to the effect is given in a form that the recipient
understands, and this acknowledges that obviously
a number of or perhaps the majority of people who are being subjected to these
orders may well have complex needs in terms of their
ability to understand, including mental health, and it
would be consistent with the approach taken in the United Kingdom to
ensure that there is a requirement that the explanation is given in
a form that the recipient can understand.
Perhaps linked also to that is the suggestion
that the person being issued with an order has
information about their right to seek legal assistance or to make a formal
complaint, including to the IPCA.
There's obvious difficulties that arise in terms of the duration
of the order and having the ability to seek advice during that time
period.
But given that
the penalties include fines for,
and potentially coming before the courts, then it
is desirable that there is a complaint pathway to an
external body included in the legislation that is separate to
the court process itself
that may arise should people ultimately become
criminalized.
The final point that we recommend
ought to be included is the provision for adequate
accountability and oversight, and we have included in our written
submissions
the proposal that an amendment to facilitate
ongoing independent oversight of police using these new
powers is included,
and that ought to include a statutory duty to record the grounds
for each order issued under Section 8A and mandatory
annual reporting to the Minister of Police and Human Rights
Commission. It is our submission that
that oversight is
essential if this bill is to go ahead.
I've rushed through. Hopefully, we do have some time for questions.
Yeah, thanks, Nicky and Debbie.
Great to have you with us. We've got a question from Tamatha Paul.
I'm
Okay.
Thank you for your submission.
My first question is just around the reasonable grounds to suspect.
Are those words or is that phrasing,
is that widespread throughout criminal law, or is this really an
outlier in terms of using that kind of wording or
giving that kind of level of freedom and discretion to a police officer to
determine?
Usually reasonable grounds to believe is the common phrase.
It's a slightly higher standard. Suspect can just be, "Oh, I've got a
feeling." But belief actually requires a bit more than that.
Requires them to actually think about it and make a decision.
So that would usually be required.
And if it is left to suspect or an
officer's feeling,
is that a situation where biases can
arise?
I believe so. And there's also no sort of chance for the person to
respond. So if someone is just sitting outside a store,
maybe just begging or just trying to find someplace warm to get out of the
rain,
and say one of the shop owners has complained to the police that this person is
begging. If the police just turn up and see somebody sitting there, they may well
just suspect that this has happened.
If that's the only standard, then they don't even need to ask the person what's
going on, right? And the person wouldn't actually have an ability to say, "Look,
I'm not doing anything. I'm just getting out of the rain."
So it doesn't actually leave the person trying to get out of the rain with
any kind of rights, with any ability to say, "Look, I'm not doing anything wrong."
Sorry, and just one other really quick question is just again on
the
fact that the distance to which someone has to move on isn't
specified. Is that
common throughout legislation, or are there other pieces of
legislation where someone is directed to do a thing but there isn't a
distance specified? Is that quite common, or is this again an outlier?
No. That
would
be an outlier. And as I said, that is inconsistent with
other jurisdictions. For example, in Western Australia,
there is more clarity and there are court decisions as well on
what
that may include. But
sorry, the
courts have had to clarify. Our submission on that is it's much more
desirable to have a specified radius or
geographical area-
Thank you
All right. Thank you-
... in the legislation to avoid this lack of clarity
And an arbitrariness in terms of how it's applied.
Mm.
Thank you.
Thanks, Nicola. And thank you, Debbie, for joining us this afternoon, and for your
written submission as well. Thank you.
Thank you.
Okay, our next submitter is Craig, and he's also going to be joining us on Zoom.
Hey, Craig.
Kia ora.
Thank you for joining us this afternoon. We've got you down for five minutes.
We've read your written submission, and please just leave some time at the end for
questions. Over to you.
Yeah. No, I strongly disagree with the legislation.
As you know, I make many submissions on neuro and disabilities,
and how it affects a person through their life.
And I think homelessness is something that many young
people with neuro disabilities often find
themselves in position. I think there's many Maori and all, which
is considering we've never returned the lands
and so forth to any degree, it's disgraceful.
From my own experience, in 2016, I had a head
injury,
and I found myself then I had a period of over three years where I
was homeless. And on my first night being
homeless, I
should state, at the time, I actually owned three properties and four
sections. So, unable to
work and in a situation, and that I found
myself moving outside one of the sections,
which on the first night I was contacted by the police, that all I'd done is gone
for a walk down the subdivision. I must've tripped a camera.
So yeah, I was questioned.
Well, one of them questioned me over and searched my vehicle.
Didn't tell me what he was doing, just went ahead and did it.
Several nights later, I was
again contacted by the police,
and they'd been contacted by FCC, who were concerned about me,
but did nothing at all to give me any help.
In that period, I went from sleeping in a vehicle, to sleeping in a
garage,
to sleeping at the local campground.
That was costing me more to sleep in a tent in a
puddle,
than the houses I actually had, that were rented out.
So yeah, I say very much about safe spaces.
And where do people go?
It's all right moving and nobody wants you here, but where do you go?
Your social responsibility fails at every single level,
and that. So you've got to take some responsibilities that if you
want to move people on, where are you going to move them onto?
A safest place or not a safe place? And I think it's a
responsibility not just as a committee of members of Parliament, but as
councils, and what churches and local iwi and
all. And where these safe spaces are, that people
can actually pull a vehicle up and actually just stay somewhere for the
night safely with their animals and possibly their children,
until there can be some social services and some services
that give some help.
Yeah, we're not really looking at the other point of view
and the other perspective of where people do go.
So maybe that should be the question of what do you provide these people to move
on to?
So that's my submission. If you've got any questions.
Thank you, Craig. I'll just look to see if there are any members who have a
question for you. Does
not appear to be the case. But we just really value both your written submission
and also for presenting to us this afternoon as well.
Thank you for joining us, Craig.
Kia ora. Thank you.
All right, members, we now have Common Grace Aotearoa.
We've got Kate and Amber who are going to present to us in person.
Kia ora koutou. Just before I begin, I have
written permission to show some artwork.
Okay.
So if just can have some team members
put that up and we'll refer to it during our submission.
Thanks, guys.
Tena koutou katoa. No Ingarangi, no Kotirana.
Ko Kate Day.
Kia ora. I'm Kate Day, one of the co-directors of Common Grace Aotearoa.
Kia ora koutou. My name is Reverend Amber Leonard-Schoss.
I'm a community chaplain here in Wellington, where for much of my adult
life, my whanau and I, as part of my church community, have
shared life and home with people who have found-- like, needed a safe
place to be. Sometimes emergency accommodation, and sometimes building life
and home together.
We're here on behalf of Common Grace, which is a movement of Christians
speaking up to transform unjust structures for the common good.
Our movement is made up of around 3,700 people from hundreds
of churches of all denominations across Aotearoa, and we speak to oppose
this bill.
Mm.
Two days ago, I was chatting before church and telling someone what I planned to
say in my submission today, and my voice was angry.
A man overheard me, and it was a man who has lived in a community
that takes in people off the street, out of homelessness.
A man who had every right to be angry about move on orders,
too. He's someone who's followed Jesus a long time.
And do you know what he said to me after all his years of living with people on the
margins? He said,
"They need love, those cabinet ministers.
They need to know that God sees them and loves them, too."
And so into a day of anger and of incredulity at what you
propose, of heartbreak that we're even having this conversation,
I offer that reminder that might just be from God,
that even cabinet ministers on the brink of making a terrible mistake
are seen, are loved by God, and they matter,
just like every person sleeping down there on Lambton Quay.
Mm.
No less, no more.
As Christians, the fact that our neighbors experience homelessness,
it concerns us deeply.
We serve a God who identifies with and prioritizes the most
marginalized groups in society and calls us to do the
same.
We know that God hears the cries of people in distress and
responds, and God calls us to do the same.
In Matthew 25, Jesus makes clear that our attitude and
responsiveness towards these groups reflects our very attitude
towards God.
God says, "Whatever you did for one of the least of these brothers and sisters of
mine, you did for me." And we feel this challenge deeply, and we
seek to respond.
At Common Grace, we've witnessed something quite unique since this government
proposed move on orders. We've had people actually phone us up,
eager to act, and we've seen thousands of people moved by
compassion to oppose this idea.
Out of prayer, we felt moved to hold an overnight vigil of solidarity
for compassionate solutions to homelessness at Wellington Cathedral of St
Paul. We had over 200 people camping down there from every denomination.
We've had churches across the country moved to gather submissions, and we've
seen young people, some of whom are here, writing submissions for the first time.
We've seen people waking up to politics for the first time.
Mm.
And I think that what that shows us, what Minister Goldsmith has achieved through
this bill,
is that it's reawakened New Zealand to its values by showing them an opposite.
New Zealanders want people in poverty to receive help.
New Zealanders don't want people kicked when they're down.
Mm.
This bill has also helped to articulate another value that we hold deeply,
that a person has no less right to exist in public space because they are
pushing all their belongings in a shopping trolley than a cabinet minister
does.
It offends the values of New Zealanders to suggest that you can shunt
someone out of public space simply for being poor.
It offends us that you propose to do that to children.
Of course, none of us want to see people sleeping in
doorways. It breaks our hearts. We want to
see actual, genuine solutions.
The shortcomings of this bill have been easy to articulate to our children, and
they understand it immediately. Children in our network have said in their
submissions, "Move people on to where?" Moving
people is not the answer.
This bill has also made it easy to articulate why we need to get involved
in politics to stop people who own many houses
from punishing people who have none.
This bill is inspiring people to tune into select committee, and this
bill is inspiring people to enroll to vote.
Yeah. And so alongside my sadness at this bill, I am hopeful
there are alternatives.
This bill has started so much more talk about them, and that is hopeful.
As part of a community that knows some of the cost of homelessness in
very real and personal ways on our skin,
we know that it's not an unsolvable story.
We have stories of hope, of housing, of healthcare and
connection. We could have more of those stories.
We could have more. There are data-driven, people-centered,
compassionate solutions.
On the banner, there's plenty of ideas that have been brought by the community at
our vigil, some of whom are frontline workers,
some of whom are rough sleeping, some from people who care about their
neighbors.
Communities like Still Waters, who will come later, that have been a place of kai
and prayer and whakawhanaungatanga in the city for decades.
It was that for me when I was a teenager that needed somewhere safe to be.
As a community, the community that includes and must include
this government, we know the kind of things that work.
The resourcing of Housing First, the need for
more addiction services, the need to solve a very practical challenge that
our larger cities have nowhere for rough sleepers to go at night to go to
sleep after hours, as even Minister Goldsmith and our Prime Minister have
learned for the very first time.
I'm hopeful. I am hopeful that we are talking about those challenges
and potential solutions because we have them.
And I'm also hopeful that move on orders will never see the light of day.
Because to pass, this idea has to get through Cabinet.
Mm.
And this bill will only pass if Minister Chris Bishop
fails to stop his legacy as housing minister being remembered for a
hated policy, and one that he has stated will likely breach the Bill of Rights.
Mm.
It will only pass if Minister Tama Potaka, who has visited rough
sleepers in Wellington, fails to stop a measure that he knows will
harm them.
It will only pass if the Honorable Louise Upston, Minister
of Disability Issues, fails to speak up for tangata
whaikaha who are disproportionately represented on our streets.
If Minister for Youth, James Mega, fails to stop a measure that will see
children, many of them abuse survivors, get entangled in the justice system
instead of given the help they need
This bill will only pass if Prime Minister Christopher Luxon fails to
lead a government who will listen to every kind of expert and to read the mood
of the public.
So throughout this bill
urgently fund and embed the solutions every frontline service
is asking you for, is telling you what is needed.
Housing first, addiction services, health services, build housing,
especially one bedroom units. People attending and watching, and I suspect that
New Zealand has never been more attuned to the injustice of homelessness or hungry
for solutions than we are as we watch the passage of this bill.
We're watching for cabinet ministers who understand they should never undermine the
dignity of their neighbors sleeping on Lambton Quay.
So we're watching, we're praying, and interested in your next
move. We're watching for leaders with compassionate solutions.
We're ready to vote.
Thank you, Kate, and thank you, Amber. We do have a couple of questions.
We're going to start with Carl Bates.
Thanks very much, Chair. And as a Christian
member of the House, I appreciate your submission
to the select committee today. I am interested, though,
in whether in the conversation you're having
about this bill,
you are
articulating all of the things that have been
done that you're referring to, like opening crisis
cafes to support those that need it, like the reduction
in rents that are the lowest increase in 25 years,
like the houses that I opened, or was at the
opening of, in Whanganui last week.
It just feels
both very judgmental
and very one-sided,
and doesn't
address the challenge
that businesses, that spaces face
across the country that are trying to serve their communities.
So just interested in whether when you are having
these discussions, you're articulating all of those things,
or if the conversation is very political and focused on this one
thing.
You want to speak, or shall I?
Thank you. So,
thanks for the question. And yet this bill.
Yeah. The progress, thank you for that. And yet this bill. Mm-hmm.
And yet this bill that undermines dignity of people.
Yeah. Thank you for the solutions. We need more. Yeah.
And the social housing register of 19,000 people
needs progress at a much faster rate. So, yeah.
Can-
So the challenges that some people are experiencing across the
country in their businesses that are creating
employment and activity-
Mm-hmm
... and paying the taxes that are enabling us to do some of the stuff,
their consideration is not something that you're willing to
have a legitimate conversation about?
We have existing
ways of trespassing people. Mm-hmm.
There are--
I want to have the conversation about how we end homelessness, and this time is
sucking up conversation that could be spent on that.
Mm-hmm.
Thank you very much.
And we've got a question here from Camilla Belich.
Thank you. And thanks for your submission, and thanks for
all of the work that you put into it through bringing the art and the
visual that you pictured in your submission as well.
I just wanted to ask around the description that you put
in around, and the recommendation around removing survival behaviors.
I don't think we've had it-
Mm-hmm
... maybe encapsulated in that way before.
I just wanted to give you opportunity maybe to talk to
why
rough sleeping, begging, and
indicating an intent to inhabit a place,
that that's kind of the right term for you to use for that
type of
concept.
I think it came from officials' advice to government.
I don't know if you want to speak particularly about those.
I think that's you, Heidi. Sure.
But for you, that's-
It's, yeah, that was the term that has come out of the-
Yeah
... the documents presented to government. Yeah.
Fantastic. Okay. Well, thank you both for joining us this afternoon and for your
written submission as well.
Okay, our next submitter is Greg, and he's going to be joining us on Zoom.
Kia ora. Can you hear me?
We can, Greg. Thank you for joining us, and sorry we're running a few minutes late.
We have read your written submission.
We've got you down for five minutes, so over to you.
Sure, no problem. So I'm Greg Presland. I'm a lawyer.
I've been practicing law in West Auckland for the last 42 years.
Ever since the Oranga Tamariki Act was passed in 1989, I've been
on the panel of lawyers or youth advocates who work for
young people who are in trouble.
I've acted for hundreds, if not thousands, of young people since
then. I tend to really like them. They're young people almost
inevitably from strange circumstances, coping with poverty, and
too many of them are Maori and Pacifica.
Youth court's system is predominantly therapeutic.
It wants to sort young people out and sort out their problems so that they
can then lead happy, constructive lives, and often it works pretty
well.
The intent of the current bill that you're considering is clearly to allow police
to
issue move-on orders requiring people engaged in disorderly or
disruptive behavior in public places to leave.
Begging and sleeping rough are included,
and up to now, these are not of themselves criminal activities.
And my submission is that the move-on orders power is not
necessary for young people between the age of 14 and 18, and
existing powers are more than sufficient
Because there's already power for police officers to intervene if they find a young
person sleeping rough or begging.
Section 48 of the Oranga Tamariki Act says that where a
young person is found
unaccompanied by a parent or guardian
in a situation in which their physical or mental
health is being, or is likely to be impaired,
a constable may
take the child and young person
and either return them home or hand them over to Oranga Tamariki,
and care and protection proceedings may then ensue.
So that's an existing power.
And being homeless is a pretty strong indicator that a young
person's physical or mental health is being, or is likely to be
impaired.
Police already have the power to deal with young people in that sort of
situation and return them home,
and my submission is they don't need the extra power which this bill intends to
give them.
And what I would pose for you as a question is, what would a responsible
police officer do
when confronted with a 14-year-old who's clearly homeless?
Would they tell them to leave the area and go elsewhere,
somewhere that's potentially less safe,
or would they try and get them home or deliver them to Oranga Tamariki?
There's other problems with the proposal.
First of all, the
power for a police officer to arrest a young person is pretty heavily
prescribed. There's all sorts of hoops that they have to jump
through,
and the process is not simple.
So I think it's going to be pretty difficult for a police
officer to
arrest a young person who may be in breach of a move on order,
even if they do breach it.
And to cap things off, there are two principles in the Oranga Tamariki Act,
which to me suggests that the chances of a
breach case ever making court is very unlikely.
First of all, unless the public interest requires otherwise, criminal
procedures should not be instituted against a young person
if there's an alternative means of dealing with the matter.
Hear, hear.
And arresting a young person only because they're homeless or being
a slight nuisance should not qualify, in my view.
And secondly, criminal proceedings should not
be instituted against a child or young person in order to give
assistance or services needed to advance their wellbeing.
Those two principles are contained in Section 208 of the Act.
So in summary, I would suggest that if a police officer finds a
young person who's homeless, they've already got power to
take them
and place them in the care of Oranga Tamariki if a parental home is not available.
That's the power that they can and should exercise,
and it's extraordinarily unlikely that an arrest would ever be
justified or charges against a young person end up in court
if they did breach this bill, if it's passed.
So my urging to you is to recommend that the bill be amended
so it doesn't apply to young people aged between 14 and 18.
Kia ora.
Thank you, Greg, and thank you for your written submission as well.
Doesn't appear that we have any questions for-
I have a question.
Oh, Tamatha Paul.
Thanks, Greg, for your submission.
One thing that I hear when people are talking about young people and the
effect that this bill has on them is, where are their parents?
And I wondered, with your decades of experience advocating for young people, if you
might want to enlighten the committee about where these kids' parents
are.
Far too many of them have families that are devastated by poverty,
and they're just coping by themselves, or they've got a split
family, or they've got family circumstances which
aren't ideal, or it's not even safe for them to go back home.
So, that just doesn't happen, and then the
state should stand up and give them care and assistance, and
there are means of doing that already.
So to
say to a police officer that they should tell this young person in these
circumstances that they've got to go elsewhere,
to me is the wrong response. It shouldn't be what they should do.
There should be a therapeutic approach instead.
Thank you.
Thank you very much, Greg, and thank you for joining us this afternoon and for your
written submission as well.
Kia ora.
All right. Our next submitter is Nikki, who's also going to be joining us on Zoom.
Kia ora, Nikki. Thank you for joining us this afternoon.
We've read your written submission, and we've got you down for five minutes.
Over to you.
Kia ora. Tēnā koutou katoa. Ko Ingarangi te whakapaparanga
mai, engari ko Aotearoa te whenua tupu,
ko Ngā Motu te kāinga, ko Nikki toku ingoa. Tēnā tātou katoa.
Thank you to the committee for the opportunity to speak to my submission today.
I'm here today to oppose this bill in its entirety, and I'll use my
time to explain why.
I speak with previous experience of supporting vulnerable people through the
healthcare systems in both Aotearoa and in the UK.
Through those experiences, I've seen firsthand what poverty and
homelessness do to a person's body and mind.
The chronic health issues, the mental health crises that spiral because there's
nowhere safe to rest. The slow erosion of dignity that comes from
being told again and again that you can't be in the place where you are or where
you found yourself.
The bill says that it will do three things.
It'll equip police to deal with public disorder, it will increase the public sense
of safety, and support urban centers and local economies.
I don't believe it will do any of these things effectively, and I'll talk through
why
First, moving people on does not resolve disorder, it relocates
it. If someone is sleeping rough outside a shop and police move them
on, they do not disappear. They walk to the next street, the next doorway, the next
town. The underlying reasons that they were there in the first place, no
housing, no income, sometimes no support network at all, travel with
them. We're not solving a problem here.
This is just creating costs for the taxpayer and the further
destabilization of people who are already in crisis.
A great many of the people that this bill will actually be used against are not
disorderly in any way. They're unsupported.
When a person in psychological distress is sleeping rough or behaving
erratically in public, a move on order does not connect them to care.
It simply pushes them out of sight, with a constable, not a clinician,
as the first and only response. That is not treatment.
It's displacement dressed up as enforcement, and it will fall
hardest on the people the mental health system has already failed to reach.
Second, on public safety, a person who's just been fined or arrested for standing
still in the wrong place is not safer, and neither is anyone around them.
What actually increases community safety is stability.
People housed, people supported and connected to services.
Criminalizing the visible symptoms of poverty doesn't make it go away.
It simply makes a punishable offense to be poor in public.
Third, on supporting urban centers and economies, retailers and city communities
are struggling with disorder, and I don't dismiss that concern.
But businesses don't want the problem just shuffled around the corner.
They want it solved, and that means investment in outreach, in
emergency and transitional housing, in addiction and mental health
services. That's what rebuilds confidence in town centers.
A move on order is not a solution. It's a postponement with a fine
attached.
I also want to just raise with the committee something they should sit with, that
homelessness in this country is growing faster than our population.
That's the emergency. Every year, this bill would mean that more people who've done
nothing wrong except run out of options are pushed into contact with
the justice system for the simple act of existing in a public space.
That pressure then lands on a corrections system that's already stretched to its
limit.
Finally, I'd ask the committee to consider the state of public trust in police
right now. Confidence has been shaken by concerns about
accountability and judgment in the use of existing powers.
Handing over broader powers to move people on at a moment when
that trust is fragile does not strengthen the relationship between
police and the communities they serve.
Those vulnerable communities, most of all.
I recognize the committee is genuinely trying to respond to real concerns from
real communities, but I would ask you to redirect that energy toward
housing, toward health, and toward addiction services, and
restoring confidence in policing rather than towards this
legislation that punishes people for the outcomes of
policy failures elsewhere.
So for these reasons, and consistent with this committee's duties under Te
Tiriti o Waitangi to uphold the health, the safety, and the well-being
of all the communities in Aotearoa, I respectfully ask that
you reject this bill. Tena koutou katoa.
Kia ora, Nicky. Thank you very much for joining us this afternoon and for your
written submission as well. We do really appreciate it.
Thank you.
Okay, our next submitter is going to be Still Waters Community Wellington, and
we've got Sasha, who's going to be presenting.
I've got two other members of the community who have joined me at the table for
today.
Fantastic. If you just want to introduce them to us.
So
Hi, I'm Larissa Ward. I'm-
Hey, Larissa.
Larissa.
You come here. And this is Tania.
Hi.
Kia ora.
Fantastic. Sasha, we've got you down for 10 minutes.
We've read your written submission, but over to you.
Awesome. Thank you. So tena koutou katoa.
Thank you for the opportunity to speak today. My name's Sasha Green.
I'm here with members of the Still Waters community, there are others
in the seats,
to express our strong opposition to the Summary Offences Orders
Amendment Bill.
Still Waters is a Christian community in inner city Wellington.
We've been around for 35 years, based in Cuba Street and
Willis Street. We aim to welcome people, give space for
people to belong and participate and care for each
other. We're a place where people who may have been excluded or
made to feel unwelcome elsewhere
to come along and contribute and have their dignity and mana
upheld. Each week, we gather for a community meal
and our inclusive expression of church.
Throughout the week, we offer practical support, advocacy, food, friendship,
and connection. Many people who are part of our community have
experienced or are currently experiencing homelessness, housing
insecurity, poverty, addiction, mental distress, and social
isolation. Those experiences shape what we want to say
today.
And we're a community of,
at any time, kind of 50 plus people.
But over those 35 years, hundreds and hundreds of people have
been part of Still Waters and impacted by it.
From our experience, people who are rough sleeping or begging are not the
problem to be solved.
Their circumstances reflect the consequences of problems our
society has failed to solve. This bill treats the
visible effects of those failures as the issue rather than addressing the
causes.
Move on orders do not create housing.
They do not provide mental health support, addiction treatment, or income.
They propose to move people on without it being clear where
those people can go and risk criminalizing poverty
and pulling people into the justice system.
When you've got nowhere to go and you're being told to move on, that doesn't
solve anything
You don't suddenly have somewhere safe to sleep.
And just like this floor, you're not welcome.
Our opposition to the bill is not about saying, "Do nothing." It is
about asking Parliament to invest in things that make a real
difference.
So we are asking you to invest in housing so people have places to
go. We want to increase the mental health,
addiction, and outreach services that people need.
And to tell you that there is a better way to
support the community-based responses where people can belong,
be treated with dignity, and get support, and an upper hand
so they can get out of these circumstances.
Because a lot of the time, people don't get enough money to get up out
of these circumstances. What you want everybody to eventually be
productive people of the community. Well, they just need the extra support.
And I've done research, like Department of Conservation, there's lots of
spare sections of land where yous could put
prefabricated
cabins on there that would be way more cheaper than buying hotels,
putting people in prison for 50,000 a pop just to get them out and
in the same
predicament. They need a lot of support. I was homeless.
I was mental. I was really sick. And just with the right people stepping in,
helping me, I got to here. And there is a lot of hope
for them.
People necessarily don't want to be stuck there with no education or not
believing in themselves. But we have this thing in society where a lot of
them are trauma patients or with mental illness, and if they can be
just dealt with the right way, they will be productive people.
Now I'm looking for work, and now I'm housed, and now I'm
on medication, and I'm in a lot better situation than I
was. And it took people like this community, and a
lot of people like yous, too. So thank you for listening to us.
So at Still Waters, we've done a lot of learning together about
creating a more caring society. We want to share some of
this to encourage you to think about a different approach than is being
proposed in the Move on Orders Bill. Annya.
Communities are stronger when we treat people with compassion,
kindness, and care. Kai matters. When people can feed
themselves and their tamariki, they can make better
decisions. When people are given the chance to participate and
contribute to society, they can belong.
Getting to know people and hearing their stories makes a difference.
Welcoming people and building relationships creates safer
communities.
Every person is worthy of compassion.
When we know someone's name, hear their story, and
recognize their humanity, we can respond with compassion and
care. Rather than pushing people aside, our Christian
faith calls us to recognize the image of God in every person,
to welcome the stranger, to stand alongside those who are
excluded, and to seek justice for those whose voices are often
ignored. These convictions shape our opposition to this bill.
We ask the committee to reject the Summary Offences
Amendment Bill. Instead, invest in housing,
support services, and communities of belonging that uphold
people's dignity and mana. Safe communities are not built
by moving people on. They're built when everyone has somewhere to
belong. Thank you for hearing our submission.
We welcome any questions.
Fantastic. Thank you very much to all of you for submitting this
afternoon. We do have a couple of questions.
We're going to start with Dan Rosewarm.
Thanks, Chair. Hey, thanks for coming today.
And
speaking to your submission,
there was one passage in your written submission that stood out for me, and that
was, "Public spaces are among the few places available
to people without homes."
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
And for someone who has no home, no stable accommodation,
and a few support networks, what role do public spaces
play in their day-to-day survival?
Well, when I was homeless, it was
the fact of being in the bush or somewhere and getting attacked,
and being too scared to be outside of the spotlight of the
camera. I never begged when I was homeless.
I didn't even know I was being paid, so I was eating out of the rubbish bin.
I didn't know anything like this. But being in front of the
camera and around the community where people could
see me made me feel safe.
Mm-hmm.
And that's a lot. I've heard of homeless people getting beaten up in the bushes,
getting robbed.
Mm-hmm.
And they're too scared. They feel like they've got nowhere to go.
So yeah.
Mm-hmm.
Thank you. And we've got a question from Rima Nakhtali.
Thank you for sharing your experience.
Ma'am, you were talking about people being able to feed their tamariki.
So I've spoken to many
restaurant owners or business owners in South Auckland that they
themselves try and help the people that are begging outside their stores.
But they're told by many people, "We want to support your
business, but we don't feel comfortable with who's
basically loitering outside your store." I'm not
saying that
people that are in those situations don't have it tough.
But what about also those people that are trying to feed their tamariki by
running a business? All they want is help with moving
on the people that are either begging outside their store
or are living there with
their blankets. What do we say to them?
Well, I reckon that there should be a rise of income so they can actually
get themself prepared for work, the clothes that they need,
the picture they need, the The phone data they need or
anything to get themselves to work.
People need a rate of the benefit to get them to be able to work
and get themselves out of that situation, even so they can
study, so they can get the right emotional support they need,
or mental stuff, and sort themselves out.
Because what I see with this is people are in such
short margin, they don't want to go and beg out front of the
shop. That is humiliating. They want to be in a better situation, but
a lot of people are so unwell that they're
self-medicating with other stuff because they don't have the right support.
So that's why you see a lot of beggars out there on the street.
It's not necessarily that they're bad people, it's that they
need a place to help them get out of that stuck situation.
Should we-
And they need a lot of healing, too
... get Pam. Did you want to add anything to that, Pam?
No, I just think that, yeah, fair enough that shop
owners, people like that, people that are coming to beg.
But for a start, safe housing
can prevent all this.
And our government-
Give some security.
I think we seem to be going backwards.
Like, you tidy up your drug addiction and all this, and then we'll put you
into a house.
These people have got nowhere to go.
And our government is making a focus on building one-bedroom houses because there's
a lot of people that find themselves homeless because kind of order for so long
is all about, of course, prioritizing family.
There's so many... But it's okay. Thank you for coming in.
Fantastic. Well-
Thank you for listening to us. You're amazing
Thank you to the three of you, and for your entire Still Waters community who've
joined you here with you this afternoon as well. So thank you for your time.
Kia ora.
Okay. Take care.
Thank you.
Kia ora. Thank you.
All right. Our next submitter is going to be Ingrid, who's going to be joining us
on Zoom.
It sounds like a bird. It sounded like a pigeon.
Hey, Ingrid.
Kia ora.
Thank you very much for joining us this evening.
We've got you down for five minutes. We've read your written submission.
Awesome.
And if you can just leave a little bit of time for questions.
Yeah. Kia ora koutou. Thank you for the opportunity to stand-
There's some lights up there
Just one moment, Ingrid. Just one moment.
Sorry about not saying-
Excuse me. We've got our submitter here. Thank you.
Over to you, Ingrid.
Thank you.
Yeah, kia ora. I believe that the intent of this amendment
is purely to protect economic interests.
Any claims of increasing the public perception of safety
are only applicable to the section of society that this government has
deemed worthy, and forgoes any empathy or support to those
highly vulnerable members of our society.
I believe that the powers given to the police are far too great.
This type of discretional power can corrupt all too quickly, and
leaves the comfort and safety of our vulnerable members of society completely
up to the level of empathy that the constable chooses to exhibit.
This leads to a huge imbalance in power, and this power imbalance becomes
dangerous and dehumanizing. We're talking about
our most vulnerable members of society, those
who are unfortunate enough not to have access to the basic necessities of a
roof over their head. Not only do we endanger these people by allowing
this disruption to occur,
but this kind of amendment strips their dignity, which further removes
any trust in the system.
Even worse is that this applies to children, and this provides police with the
power to place move on orders on those as young as 14 years
old. 14 years old is still a child,
and how can we, as a society, choose to not only turn our backs
on these children in the first place, but then be so unfeeling
as to have the audacity to take punitive action toward them because they have no
roof over their head?
The list of offenses for which this applies is an
indictment on the lack of empathy displayed throughout.
To group threatening and disorderly behavior with those simply existing in the only
space they've found is heartless and really brings us to the crux
of this amendment, which is that this amendment seeks to justify
cruel behavior toward our most vulnerable, sanctioned by the state
to appease affronted business owners.
The new offenses carry fines completely at odds with who we are talking about.
Punitive recourse for someone
merely unfortunate enough to be homeless is pointless.
These people are there because of circumstance,
and the idea that a fine would,
A, stop them sleeping rough, or B, be within the realms of
possibility to repay, is ludicrous.
It becomes just another way in which life is made so much harder.
And all for what? So that a person so fortunate enough to own
a business can walk into their work without having to concern themselves with the
plight of those less fortunate? How Dickensian is that?
At no point is any mention made of alternatives to placing a move
on order, of referrals to support services, of transportation to
safe areas or support entities, or provision of any help
whatsoever, be it short or long-term.
And unfortunately, because this kind of state support is already lacking,
our homeless population is increasing.
The fact that these orders move someone on for up to 24 hours
proves to me that it's purely an exercise in optics.
Behavior is disrupted, but it's not altered by any form of help or
support. This amendment is a
dangerous and cruel step to take against our most vulnerable.
It actively removes power from our people and places it in the
discretionary hands of the police, an entity plagued by multiple issues,
including corruption, as recent reports have shown.
Ultimately, we need to remember that- That there but for fortune go you or I.
A society is judged on its treatment of our marginalized, vulnerable members,
and we should be striving to protect these people, not to cause further persecution
and harm.
I hope that this amendment is rejected in full,
and perhaps our nation's efforts could instead focus on
providing the support needed for all members of our society to flourish.
Nga mihi, thank you.
Thanks, Ingrid. We've got a question from Carl Bates.
Thanks, Chair. Thanks for your submission.
You made a comment that there's been no mention around the support that
people need in these situations, and I wondered if you'd read
the original
PR from the minister that said, "Naturally, every situation will be
different. Some people may require support services, some may not.
Police have the expertise to assess and determine what support is required,
if any. They do this every day." And then it goes on to
talk further about how police can support using these orders,
people to be connected with housing and other
social services, et cetera. So just wondering if you read that.
Yeah, look, I think firstly, I would say that it is naive to believe that
every police officer who is able to come into contact with people that
we're talking about here is going to exercise, firstly, the option
to help in the ways that you just talked about.
And secondly, I'd say that if that was the intent of the government, then that
should be the amendment we're making.
The amendment should be that police officers are out there providing
support to people rather than providing punitive action and removing
them from the only safe place that they are in.
Fantastic. Well, thank you very much, Ingrid.
Really appreciate both your written and oral submission with us today. Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you for hearing me.
Okay, our next submitter is Ben, who's going to be joining us in person.
Thank you, Chair.
Thanks, Ben. We've got you down for five minutes.
We've read your written submission as well. Over to you.
Kia ora.
My name is Ben, Ben Tuivawae-Jenkins.
First of all, this is a submission as an individual.
I am not someone who is particularly politically
active, although I did feel compelled to submit on this bill for the
reasons I will outline.
Now, I'm not going to labour the point of it.
You will have heard this dozens of times today, but to me, the bill seems
like it is simply an attempt to criminalize homelessness.
Put simply, as others have said, being homeless in itself is
not disorderly or disruptive behavior, which is what the
bill ought to prevent.
Now, I've lived in Wellington for almost eight years.
During that time, I have met lots of different people across the city,
including people who are homeless, and I can honestly
say these people don't want trouble.
And
from the papers that I've read in relation to this bill, I can't seem
to find any evidence to the contrary.
The only disorderly behavior I have seen in relation to homeless people is
where they're actually being threatened by the likes of drug dealers,
which brings me onto my next point, which is that I think the
bill is putting people at risk. I think,
as one of the previous speakers said, that
the bill is claiming that it will increase the public's sense of
safety.
But aren't those who are living on the streets
members of the public?
And if so, by making that claim, it doesn't seem to make
sense to me because, as has been said,
you have this situation where you're moving someone on from a
public area, which is well documented as
somewhere where people want to stay to be safe,
and you're simply forcing them out of those areas and making them more vulnerable.
So instead of increasing the public safety,
what you're doing is simply through this bill, in my view, is jeopardizing it.
Not only that, but I think by issuing a move on order, you're potentially
preventing someone from being able to access health and support services,
which may often, as is the case here in Wellington, be centrally located.
My third point is that the bill seems to lack any real support as far as I've
been able to tell of the government agencies that were consulted.
None appear to have expressed support for the proposal, and some have actively
opposed it.
Not only that, but the Ministry of Justice itself has concerns around
the bill and didn't recommend the proposed approach due to the
intrusion into rights of freedom, which I also note the Attorney General
has also commented on.
I think that with the lack of consultation with those mental health and social
service providers
kind of to me says that there is an issue with this sort of being rushed
through. I think it's criminalizing homelessness by
stealth.
I think this is also apparent from the fact that it
seems that there was an initial failure to consult Crown Law on the addition of
rough sleeping, which seems to have been slipped into the bill at some point.
And like I say, I think Ingrid hit the
nail on the head when she said it's Dickensian, really.
So what I ask is why has the bill been introduced in
its current form? The minister himself said in the Cabinet paper that,
quote, "Applying move on orders to begging may impact on the ability for those
experiencing homelessness to meet basic living expenses."
So why do it? It just seems like
a bizarre thing to do to include begging and
rough sleeping in something that it just doesn't need to be in
there. No one is disputing the need for us all to be able to
enjoy public spaces without the risk of intimidation, but
this is not the way to go about it.
So I
urge you to reject the bill or otherwise amend it
so that we're not penalizing those without shelter.
Thank you.
Fantastic, Ben. And thank you for your really clear submission, particularly what
you've just presented to us. So thank you for joining us this evening and for
sitting in the gallery as well.
Thank you very much.
Thank you. All right. We're going to be joined by Durham Street Methodists,
Pauline and Danielle. Daniella, sorry,
who are going to join us on Zoom.
From your pad, Mr. Webb.
Yeah.
Hello.
Hey, Pauline. Thank you very much for joining us this evening.
We've read your written submission. We've got you down for 10 minutes.
Just leave some time for questions.
Okay. Thank you.
Daniella is not joining me. She's unwell.
Tena koutou, tena koutou katoa.
The Christchurch Central Methodist Parish, we're more commonly known as
Durham Street Methodists, is an inner city parish of the
Ōtautahi Christchurch for Te Hahi Weteriana
o Aotearoa, the Methodist Church of New Zealand.
We aspire to be a faith community committed to open hearts,
open minds, and open doors.
In our strategy, we are committed to connect, collaborate, and
grow mana-enhancing relationships with others, especially
those who are marginalized.
As an inner city church, we have considerable interaction with
homelessness, directly and through our connection with the
Christchurch Methodist Mission, which provides significant
housing and other support across the city and beyond.
The social services division of the mission is housed in our
center, and that includes the youth housing project,
and several Alcoholics Anonymous and Narcotics Anonymous
groups also operate from it.
Our concerns.
We wish to express our opposition to the Summary Offences
Move On Orders Amendment Bill.
We join with faith leaders across numerous churches who
have already expressed their opposition to the bill.
Our faith calls us to uphold the dignity of every
person and to seek justice and compassion in public life.
We believe this bill risks undermining those values
by expanding police powers in ways that could
disproportionately affect vulnerable communities.
The bill also has the potential to capture more
people in the criminal justice system, including
those as young as 14 years old, which can cause
long-term damage.
It is no solution to homelessness, mental
illness, addiction, or poverty.
Shifting a problem around is not a decent response.
Neither is trying to make it less visible.
In an earlier submission for the Retailers Federation, she said they
will just move to another doorway.
There are already powers under the Summary
Offences Act to deal with disorderly behavior and offensive
behavior that significantly disrupts public order and
prevent members of the public going about their normal
activities. In contrast, this bill is
not restricted to people behaving in an offensive or disorderly
way. Indeed, the bill risks making poverty,
addiction, mental illness, and homelessness
worse and more difficult to address.
It will put vulnerable homeless at greater risk as they
have to move away from what may be positively
relatively safer places into more isolated
and less safe spaces.
Many of the rough sleepers are women
and/or vulnerable people of all ages.
It will make it harder for social workers and volunteers from
the various charities and groups who try to rehouse the
homeless to stay in touch with them.
Where the police are to move them onto is unclear.
Our understanding is that the night shelter in Christchurch is full
most nights.
We also support an evidence-based approach to public
policy and are troubled by the widespread
expert opposition to this bill.
The Christchurch Methodist Mission, which is part of Housing First
Ōtautahi, has successfully housed over 500
people who have experienced long-term homelessness,
and many other social service organizations with
frontline experience tell us the proposed bill will
not work.
The attorney general has officially reported that at least two
aspects of the proposed bill are inconsistent
with the New Zealand Bill of Rights
Act. The Ministry of Justice, in its regulatory impact
statement, does not favor the proposed bill and advises
that its costs are likely to outweigh benefits.
In particular, it assesses that potential benefits to
the public are unclear, with the costs mainly
falling on public services and those issued with move on
orders.
Instead, it prefers the status quo as more cost
effective.
The Ministry of Housing and Urban Development strongly advised
against including begging, rough sleeping, and other
survival behaviors in the bill.
It also warned of the safety risks of forcing rough
sleepers, particularly women and young people, out of safer,
well-lit public spaces into more isolated
areas. It advises that law enforcement
is an inappropriate and ineffective response to homelessness.
In particular, the criminal records often limit the
availability of housing solutions and risk
further entrenched homelessness.
Oranga Tamariki
and youth advocates have warned the bill will criminalize
vulnerable children and young people.
The Police Association are concerned that the bill will drain
limited police resources, and notes that there are already
laws in place to deal with disorderly behavior.
Our Wesleyan tradition teaches that faith must be active in
love and justice. We are called to stand with those who
are marginalized and to challenge systems that
perpetuate inequality. The bill,
even if well-intentioned, would likely harm those
already vulnerable and struggling at society's edges.
Our vision for public spaces instead is of places of
encounter, dialogue, and care where all people can
gather safely and freely.
Rather than restricting movement, we urge
Parliament to invest in community-based solutions that
address the root causes of poverty, homelessness,
insecurity, and disconnection.
Our recommendations. We oppose the bill in the
spirit of open hearts, open minds, and open doors.
We respectfully ask the Justice Committee to reject
this bill. Instead, we encourage continued
dialogue with faith communities, social service
providers, and those most affected to craft
legislation that promotes inclusion, compassion,
and genuine public safety. Many of those
groups have actually made submissions
to this bill. However,
if it is still to proceed, we strongly urge Parliament at
least to remove survival behaviors, such as
begging and rough sleeping, from the bill.
In any case, additional resources are needed for
addiction health, mental health, and
emergency housing, and public and
community housing at scale.
Further, the government should implement duty to assist
legislation so that we have an obligation
to do what we can to prevent homelessness and
work with people to find them suitable and stable
housing with wraparound support when
required.
That's the end of our submission.
Thank you, Pauline, and thank you for joining us this evening.
And we don't have any questions for you, so thank you very much for your
submission.
Thank you.
Okay, our next submission is from St Peter's on
Willis Social Justice Group, in person Gail.
Thank you for joining us. We've read your written submission.
We've got you down for 10 minutes.
Thank you.
And just leave a little bit of time for questions.
Oops.
Kia ora. And thank you Tom Rutherford for
introducing me. My name is Gail Duncan, and
I chair the Social Justice Group of St Peter's Anglican Church, Te Aro,
Wellington.
And with me is Elsa Cornell, one of our Social
Justice Group members.
We are on a social justice mission, which St Peter's has long pursued, to
enable justice and consideration of current issues from a
Christian perspective.
St Peter's on Willis Social Justice Group requests that the
Summary Offences Move On Orders Amendment Bill is rejected in its
entirety.
We wish to highlight to the Justice Committee that this bill impinges
on human rights in criminalizing the predicament
of those who have no choice at the time concerned in
terms of options of accommodation but to rough sleep.
They must inhabit a public place, and they may need to
beg. Move on orders permit arrest
without a warrant, thus we are all at risk of being
imposed upon to leave a specified
area for a specified amount of time up to 24 hours.
We share the concerns of the Attorney General regarding
freedom of expression and freedom of movement.
We wish to point out if anyone is displaying
disorderly, disruptive, threatening, or intimidating
behavior in a public place, laws already
exist to deal with this without overriding human
rights.
We draw to your attention
mothers and children with behavior indicating an intent
to inhabit a public place
have nowhere else to go due to
discrimination and lack of resources.
Young people aged 14 to 25 and
children under 14 years old make up almost
half the homeless Other sources note that
LGBTQ are over-represented, and there
are a growing number of elderly, my age or older,
unable to find housing and forced to beg and live on the street.
In the 2023 census, more women than
men were reported to experience homelessness,
many with babies and young children in tow,
escaping abusive relationships.
This bill constitutes a further act of violence,
this time by the state.
Is it the intention of the government to create
criminals of the destitute?
The Social Justice Group cannot find any good reason to
support any feature in this bill.
The intention of the Minister of Justice to implement Option
Four disregards the regulatory impact statement advice
from the Ministry of Justice, which prefers the status quo.
Matthew 26:11 tells us that there will always be the
poor.
This doesn't mean we sweep the disadvantaged away
or lack compassion to work with them, but instead
confirms that we have a continuing duty to aid the poor.
Coalition priorities since December 2023
to balance the books have disempowered people's economic
security and reduced investment by government and
services, and this has human costs, which is
evidenced in the rise in homelessness that we see now,
noting our inflation rate is now 4.1%.
Yes.
The number of persons in emergency accommodation
has been dropped to meet government targets.
Public servants are expected to meet those
emergency housing reduction
targets. What happens to the people who don't get
listed anymore? It is totally
irresponsible to address a government policy
failure by proposing move-on orders
applying to persons 14 years and older, including a
criminal offense, a criminal offense, for non-compliance,
when you know perfectly well those affected will be unable to
pay the fines, leaving only one door open to accommodation,
prison.
Is the cost of imprisoning a person, we quoted
150,000 per annum, and perhaps this should be corrected to
120,000, it's still a lot, preferred to
building social housing and providing better access to
social services?
We would like to draw your attention to the regulatory impact, Clause
61. There is also risk that move-on
orders will merely shift concerning behaviors to other
areas and displace the people to whom they are applied.
I've been in Perth very recently,
for eight days, where they have move-on orders.
All that has happened is
that the people are moved on into the suburbs like West Perth and
Subiaco,
where they haunt the doorways of stores and create
discontent or concern for the public.
My son
escorted both myself and my husband just two blocks in
West Perth, and we've never had to have that done to us
before because the people had shifted into the suburbs.
That's all that happened. You shifted the problem.
There are other policy solutions which would place the
wellbeing of all persons concerned, including shopkeepers,
like investing and supporting the homeless, thus improving public
health in the areas concerned, and the health and
prospects of the homeless to have secure accommodation
with facilities.
Investment in services to address circumstances
leading people to destitution, rampant poverty, and the
tragedy of poverty in children is urgent.
Data showing levels of poverty must be generated by the
government.
St Peter's on Wallis Social Justice Group rejects this bill and
recommends that the government respects those that are in
circumstances of homelessness and pursues avenues of
provision for their wellbeing, respecting their preferences
for sometimes disengaging from the social welfare system, or
difficulty accessing it, or wishing to be separate from regular
social housing.
To conclude, the government must acknowledge this bill
represents intrusion into the freedom of expression and
freedom of movement,
and right to be free from arbitrary detention, which
constitutes a compelling reason to reject this bill.
Finally, to quote Cardinal Roger Mahony,
1998,
"Any society, any nation, is judged on the basis
of how it treats its weakest members, the last, the least,
and the littlest." Thank you.
Thank you, Gail. We've got a question from Dan Rosewood.
Thanks, Chair. Thanks for that submission.
You highlighted that almost half of those experiencing
homelessness are under 25.
Yes.
And I was just wondering, what concerns do you have about applying move-on
orders and criminal penalties to young people, particularly
those who may already be vulnerable or
disconnected from support?
Well, we're very concerned that
people between 14 and 25 or under 14
would be placed in circumstances,
well, the 14 to 25-year-olds, where basically you are
extinguishing their future prospects by putting them in
circumstances where firstly they're moved and recorded, then perhaps
there's an objection or
They enter the
justice system, the remand system.
Mm-hmm.
It makes it extremely difficult for them and older people
to be able to gain accommodation, to even be considered for it, and to be
considered for a job. But to put that burden on people between
14 and 25, because they were in
circumstances probably well outside their control, is just
completely against any form of social
responsibility.
Thank you. Thank you, Gail, and thank you very much for joining us this evening,
and for your written submission as well. Thank you.
Do you have time for me to make a couple of points?
If they're quick, yes.
Sure.
Well, it wasn't long ago that the whole country was shocked
by the abuse in care report.
Mm.
And
a lot of the people who are suffering
from mental health problems and inability to adjust to
society are people who have suffered abuse,
either in those circumstances or from their
own families.
I
think that it's important to remember
their helplessness.
And secondly, I'd like to take up a point that a
former submitter made,
the
effect on the police. In New Zealand, we
have
a police service
that is very
adapted to helping people in
an empathetic way.
I lived in the United States for a number of years, and
that's certainly not the experience of the people of the police
there.
And I would hate to see the police brutalized
by
the experience of having to take steps that they
know are antipathetic to
the welfare of the people that they're dealing with.
I would hate to see the character of the New Zealand police changed
and
for the worse.
Thank you very much. Thank you. Thank you both for joining us this evening.
We appreciate it.
We've now got the Salvation Army, Ian and Paul.
Thanks for the water.
Thanks, Ian and Paul. You've obviously been watching how this has been going.
So you've got 10 minutes. Over to you.
Kia ora. Tēnā koutou katoa. Ko Ian Hutson ahau.
And this is Paul.
As you will see by looking at our
submission, we oppose this bill, and we're
recommending, or should we say pleading,
that the government focus on proven and effective
responses to homelessness that offer homes and
support to move to,
instead of orders to move on.
We come from a background of providing
a wide range of housing related services.
We have a big number of social houses,
transitional housing, plus we have community services
which offer spiritual and welfare support
towards housing.
So we've got a lot of experience in working with a range
of issues that are connected to homelessness.
We think this legislation is harmful and
it's unnecessary legislation. I've heard
others speak of that. Powers to deal with disorderly
behavior already exist,
and treating people who are sleeping rough or begging
as offenders
adds to harm to already challenging lives.
And it works against the efforts of other government
departmental ministers
in charge of welfare support and providing housing solutions.
So it's working against what the government
ideally is seeking to achieve.
There's a disproportionate impact on Maori.
Almost half of the people the Salvation Army works with are
Maori, and a high proportion of those are experiencing
homelessness.
Move on orders will increase the harm being
experienced by this cohort, these people.
And on top of that,
our concern is the way that children and youth are being targeted in
this particular legislation.
That is especially distressing because
children under 18
have less access to social support and
assistance, and there's very little in the way of specialized housing
support. So those are some of the things
about our key reasons for opposing
this. I want to hand over to Paul now to just say a few
words from here.
Yeah.
I think excuse me.
It's important to recognize this bill's coming at a time when we're dealing with
rising homelessness in this country.
Over the past two years,
we've been working with other NGO organizations to report
on the surge in
homelessness we've seen around the country.
It
comes at a time when we're facing a combination of reduced access to social
housing and withdrawal of government support for people
facing homelessness.
Less money is being spent on programs that can reduce homelessness, such
as Housing First and transitional housing, and
considerably less is being spent on emergency housing support, and the withdrawal
of that money has not been channeled into other, more effective homelessness
prevention responses. And most of the regions we're working
with report homelessness has increased,
and nowhere reports the signs of sustained
reduction. Social housing numbers are not
increasing fast enough to make an impact on housing need, people waiting
for social housing.
And private rentals remain unaffordable, even if rent
increases in some regions are slowing.
Three out of 10 renter households are paying more than 40%
income on housing and are struggling then with all the pressures around
maintaining sustaining tenancies.
We want to emphasize tonight that,
and really plead with Parliament,
there are other alternatives to doing this.
We do not need this legislation. What we need
is to really invest in the alternatives that work.
Coordinated and regional housing responses to increase the supply of
social and affordable housing. We need
the kind of assertive outreach that gets beside
people in their current need and builds relationships and
seeks solutions, doesn't try to move them on.
We need the safe drop-in spaces where people can find social support
and services, and can be connected with the services that can make a
difference for them.
We need flexible and responsive housing support that
meets the range of needs that we're seeing presenting to us all the time at The
Salvation. Young people needing help, women with children, people with
chronic addictions.
And beside the housing needs to come those wraparound services
to address the complex situations that we're seeing people presenting with in many
ways.
We'd like to see, rather than this
call to move on, the duty of care honored,
that we don't release people from prison into homelessness.
The people leaving emergency departments
don't go into homelessness. People in mental health services don't find
themselves released into homelessness.
The young people leaving care then face homelessness.
These are the things we need to work on, and
we plead with Parliament not to proceed with this bill and
address the real solutions.
Fantastic. Thank you, Ian and Paul.
Just see if-- We've got a question from Camilla Belich.
Thank you for your submission and also for all the work that you do in this area
around New Zealand,
and also that's detailed in your written submission.
And thanks for your comments around
what you think that we should be looking at more in the future and under the
current state of-
Mm
... homelessness in New Zealand. I was just wondering,
just thinking through, if I was in your shoes, what
steps would
the Salvation Army need to take if these were put in place to kind of
try and, perhaps, address a need of a
community that might be more desperate than it is currently or
may feel more at risk?
Well, I mean, there's--
And simply,
it's already a struggle,
and I think you're going to have to be thinking about where people, how you
find, how do you reach out to people who may be moved on
into
different contexts and places where maybe there's no support at all.
So that's one of the challenges that we can see straight away in this.
Yeah. I'm sorry, I didn't quite catch the question. So...
That's fine. I think you're covered.
Good enough answer. Yeah.
Fantastic. Thank you both for joining us this evening.
I really appreciate your written submission and the oral submission as well.
Thank you.
All right. Thank you.
Okay, members, our last submitter before the dinner break is Kathy, who is going to
be joining us on Zoom.
Tena koutou katoa. Ko Kathy Voyles toku ingoa, and I'm
here with our chair, Shirin Brown.
Greetings from the beautiful Waiheke Island.
Oh, is it... Okay.
There we go, Kathy.
Sorry. Okay, do I have to do that again? No.
Did you hear me at all?
We did. We did.
We did. Waiheke's beautiful.
So greetings from our beautiful island, where we also have homeless
whanau. And we do our best to help them, but high
rents and few rentals and very few government housing
makes everybody's life very difficult.
We have plenty of houses, and yet,
most of them are empty for 80% of the year.
So we're from Protect Our Gulf. It's an environmental group that
works to benefit the protection of peoples and environment on
Waiheke, and we're involved in a number of social, cultural, sustainable,
environmental initiatives.
And I, of course, speak from a position of extreme privilege
because I'm in a warm house.
I slept quite badly last night thinking about
presenting this. But I know there are thousands of our
people all over the country who have no
bed to go to tonight. They'll be sleeping on
cold, hard surfaces or in light
tents in places where they shouldn't be. There is no warm bed.
There is no kitchen. There is no toilet.
There is no
nothing. They are the people who have our lease.
So we absolutely oppose this amendment in its
entirety.
We are failing, we believe, our most vulnerable.
Indeed, this amendment would punish our
most vulnerable, and is it not enough that they're already
being punished enough and that they lack the most basic of things?
No shelter, no possessions, no fixed abode, no warmth
at night, no bathroom.
Each of these people have histories and reasons why they
have no roof over their head. I spend four to eight
hours every week in the city. I get to speak to quite
a few of them, and as our previous people have said, they have
multiple issues, psychological, physical,
addictions. It's just the
most basic thing they need is a roof over their head, and then we need to
address the other things that
are making their lives so difficult.
Now, I just want to point out that we are a signatory to the
Universal Declaration on Human Rights 1948,
and at the very least, our government, any government,
should be aiming for housing our people.
Mm-hmm.
This is an extremely important
Universal Declaration of Human Rights that we have signed up to, and
this problem is solvable, absolutely
solvable. And here, I'll come back to the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights again, and I have taken quite a few things from
the last report that was done in 2020
about the situation of housing in New Zealand, where the
Special Rapporteur said that we were in crisis then,
2020, 2021.
And that report gave the government a number of
things to work on, which unfortunately seem to be
failing at the moment. But I would call upon
this government and any other government to immediately
set up a cross-party crisis management for the
people who are homeless now. And that would be putting up
urgent shelters in our city centers while we work
on a long-term strategy
to prevent homelessness. Because we need solutions, we
don't need punishment. We don't need to criminalize these
people. They have nothing. They are the most vulnerable
of us. And yet, at the moment, of course,
this
proposed legislation was put forward, I believe, for
the embarrassment of this government of seeing tourists, seeing shoppers and
commuters seeing these people in our city centers.
And we all feel
dreadfully for those people, and it makes most of us, I'm
pretty sure, feel psychologically rather ill, seeing them
lying on the street with so little.
And I do thank the City Mission in Auckland, which has set up the
fabulous HomeGround, which I don't know if many people there have
actually visited. But what I think we need is a
HomeGround in every suburb in Auckland
and a HomeGround in so many other places.
That's apartments, wraparound services, and it's
so important what they provide at HomeGround.
It really is one of the best examples.
So I'm not going to talk in depth about what the Special
Rapporteur said, Leilani Farha in 2020,
2021. But one of the very basic things
that she did state is because we've signed up to various
treaties, including the International Covenant on
Economic, Social and Cultural Rights,
that sets out as a basic thing
adequate housing in Article 11. So pursuant
to that covenant, New Zealand has the obligation to
progressively realize the right to adequate housing
through appropriate measures. And that is also not only a roof,
but actually somewhere that provides security,
peace, and dignity. So,
I think it's pretty obvious that we do not support this amendment, and I'm really
happy to take any questions about that,
and a way forward. Because really, as it's such a crisis
point for those people in the middle of our winter.
Even in Auckland, it's very cold out there, and in other
places much worse. So thank you for listening to me, and
thank you for hearing us, and I'm happy to take questions.
Thank you, Cathy. It doesn't look like any members of the committee have a question
for you. So we're really grateful for your written submission and for presenting
with us this evening. So thank you for your time.
Thank you.
Thank you. I can also send in all those little UN things that I'm not sure,
maybe the committee's already read them, that report.
You'd be more than welcome to.
Okay.
Absolutely.
Will do. Thank you very much.
Thank you, members. We will be breaking for the dinner break.
We'll be back at 7:00 p.m.
は い 。
There we go. Hi, Irene. Thank you very much for joining us
this evening.
We have read your written submission. We've got you down for five minutes.
You'll see there's a timer. If you just leave a little bit of time for questions as
well, please. But over to you.
Kia ora koutou.
I'm
making this submission not as an expert
in rough sleeping, and I'm
not speaking on behalf of rough sleepers.
But through my
work at Ponsonby Baptist Church, I've come to know a number of rough
sleepers and their issues, and I'm very
concerned about this bill and the punitive nature of
this bill in relation to rough sleepers and the effect
on their mental health. So almost all
of the rough sleepers I've met have significant mental
health issues, and
for many reasons, they are unable to live in
accommodation at this point of time.
So they
have to find somewhere safe
to stay at night. That's really important to them, and the move on
order is likely to have a really detrimental effect on their
mental health.
I notice in the bill, one of the things that really concerns me about this
bill is that disorderly or disruptive behavior
is just rough sleeping. They don't have to be abusive to
passersby or shopkeepers. They just have to be rough sleeping,
and I think that's unnecessarily punitive for a
number of rough sleepers who are not causing any problems to anybody.
So
if they
are forced to move on,
and they don't feel safe moving on, so they return to the
place where they feel safe, they're going to be fined.
Well, first of all, they have to give information to a police officer
at peril of $500 if they don't give that information.
And giving personal information to many rough sleepers is
incredibly traumatic. So that's
likely to be a problem. And secondly, if they
don't obey the move on order, they're going to be fined up to
$2,000. Well, very few rough sleepers have
access to $2,000. So the alternative
is then three months in prison. And I don't have to
tell you the detrimental effect that prison is likely to have
on the mental health of rough sleepers.
There are alternatives. I know in
Auckland, a group of businessmen who have combined together to
get a security officer who has got to know
the rough sleepers and who
gently moves them on in a positive way to areas that are more
appropriate, and that is working well.
Now, not all businesses can afford to hire a security
officer, but I think that the government would be better to spend
money on supporting those organizations
that
get to know rough sleepers and can address and help to address
their needs, rather than the huge cost of putting them in prison
for three months, which is the likely outcome.
So,
I
do know of people personally who've been rough sleepers, who have then
been supported into accommodation and who
now live Productive lives in the community and
volunteer in all sorts of other situations as
well. So I just want to finish with
the quote that I'm sure many of you will be familiar with,
most likely attributed to Nelson Mandela, or most accurately attributed
to Nelson Mandela, when he says, "A nation should not be judged
by how it treats its highest citizens, but its lowest
ones."
Right, that's it.
Thanks, Irene. I've got a question from Dan Rosewarne.
Yeah. Hey, thanks for your submission, Irene.
You say in your submission that many of the rough sleepers you have come to
know have complex circumstances, often
mental health issues as well.
Yeah.
I was just wondering, in your experience, what kinds of
support have been the most helpful to them?
They've got to get to know and trust
the person who is trying to support them.
Trust is a huge issue for rough sleepers.
And once trust is established, I think there's a
potential to be able to bring in the
groups of people that can help them with their mental health issues.
But I'm not an expert on mental health.
Thanks, Irene.
Thank you, Irene. Thank you very much for your submission and for joining us this
evening.
Great. Thank you.
Okay, now we have the Anglican Diocese of Wellington, who are joining us
in person.
Thank you very much. We've read your written submission.
We've got you down for 10 minutes, just leave a little bit of time for
questions.
Kia ora koutou katoa,
. Thank you for giving us this time.
Just to introduce ourselves, this is Bishop Anna.
She's Assistant Bishop of Wellington. I'm Justin.
I'm the Senior Bishop of Wellington. We represent the Wellington Diocese.
Also we're here not just representing the Wellington Diocese,
we've both spent decades journeying alongside people,
young people and homeless people, particularly in Auckland, Whanganui, and
Wellington. And so we've spent time with these people as our friends, family, and
often as flatmates, et cetera. So we bring in that perspective as well.
Kia ora koutou. We know that you've already heard from many others from
across the Christian tradition, and they have shared with you our belief
that every person has inherent dignity and value.
They've also shared with you that the Jesus we follow treated those
that his own society discarded and disregarded
in complete contrast to the way that his society treated them, with compassion,
with dignity, and with care. We follow the Jesus who declared
that he had come to bring good news to the poor.
We follow the Jesus who, when called upon by a beggar in the street, did
not silence that beggar like others in the crowd tried to, but instead
invited that beggar to come forward and said, "What do you want me to do for you?"
And in response to the beggar's reply, Jesus healed him from his blindness.
Our faith calls us, as followers of Jesus, to respond to
those in need, those in poverty, those in distress with
the same way that Jesus did, with compassion, with care,
and with dignity.
And while our faith provides us with a very strong basis for opposing this bill,
the main reasons that we
oppose it are on the grounds of common sense and on the ground of the
common good.
We want public spaces that are safe places for people.
The Summary Offences Act already contains offenses
for disorderly and aggressive behavior.
They are offenses because there is a real risk of harm to people
or property, and the police already have the powers that they
need to deal with such behaviors. The only new
behaviors, I'm using inverted commas here, being targeted
by the proposed bill are begging, rough sleeping, and an intention to
inhabit the public space. These are not a threat to
public safety. This bill treats the visible
presence of poverty as the problem rather than harmful behavior.
It shifts the focus from public safety to public
discomfort. And it appears that that is what this bill is really
about, appeasing our discomfort.
Because it's uncomfortable to see a fellow human being sleeping on a
park bench when many of us have a private, safe, and secure place to
return to each night. It is uncomfortable to see another human
being begging for spare change or a scrap of food as we
go about our business.
We should be discomforted by this reality, and we ought to
respond.
But how we choose to collectively respond in our discomfort says a lot
about who we are as a society.
This bill suggests that an appropriate response to a 14-year-old who is rough
sleeping or begging is to hand them a piece of paper that tells them to
move on, and to charge that 14-year-old if they fail to comply with that
order. That's not common sense. If a young person
is rough sleeping or experiencing deprivation to the extent that
they are begging, asking them to move on or charging them
for non-compliance ignores and further compounds that young person's
vulnerability.
Common sense says that if a 14-year-old is rough sleeping or begging, we ought
to be concerned about their care and protection.
Common sense suggests that the young person should be offered appropriate social,
wellbeing, and housing support. It's in the young person's best
interest, but it's also in the best interest of the common good to take
early preventative action that reduce the likelihood that young
person will experience long-term homelessness and all the
likely consequences of that, unemployment, poverty, addiction, poor
mental and physical health. Unfortunately, that's what the evidence
says are the predicted outcomes for young people experiencing
housing insecurity, especially for those who've been in state care
That same common sense principle applies to adults who are rough sleeping or
begging. Handing them a piece of paper that tells them to move on
does nothing to address the circumstances that led them there in the
first place, nor does it provide a bed, a meal, a friend,
mental health support, addiction treatment, or a pathway to housing.
What it does do is undermine the very initiatives that are already in place to
provide essential support
by shuffling the poor from one street to another.
That's not common sense.
Common sense tells us that if we want fewer people sleeping rough
or begging, we should continue to invest in the things that have proven to
reduce homelessness and poverty, stable housing, effective social
support, accessible health and addiction services, and support for at-risk children
and young people. The government claims it wants to invest in
solutions that actually work and are effective.
You have heard over and over again in these submissions from experts
telling you what the evidence is. Housing first works.
Providing accessibility to health and addiction services works.
Offering social supports work. The common good is
not served by making vulnerable people less visible.
It is served by reducing the vulnerability itself.
Public spaces become safer, not because we have moved people on, but
because more people have safe places to go.
Every day, on our streets, we come face to face with vulnerable
people facing poverty and homelessness, and we get to choose how we
respond.
This bill asks us to respond to begging and rough sleeping by
removing it from sight. We believe New Zealand can do better than that.
We can choose responses that are practical, evidence-based, and humane.
We can choose responses that promote the flourishing and well-being of
individuals and whanau while strengthening our communities.
Whether we approach this from a faith perspective or simply ordinary
common sense, the conclusion is the same.
This bill risks criminalizing vulnerability rather than responding to
it.
As we were preparing for today, I sat with this issue and I was
drawn to a parable or a story of Jesus.
It's been a while, so I may have got a few of the words a bit wrong, and I may be
showing a little bit of improvisation here.
But a religious leader, say a bishop, went to Jesus and said, "How would
you define a neighbor?"
Jesus answered by telling a story.
"There was a man traveling from Newtown to Thorndon.
On the way, he was attacked by robbers.
They took his clothes, they beat him up, and they went off, leaving him
half dead in the city. Luckily, a member of
parliament was on his way down the same road, but when he saw him, he
moved him on.
Then a member of parliament showed up.
Again, he also moved him on. A gang member
traveling the road came on him. When he saw the man's condition, his
heart went out to him. He gave him first aid, disinfecting and
bandaging his wounds. Then he lifted him into his ute, led him to an
Airbnb and made him comfortable. In the morning, he took out
$1,000," don't know where he got it, "and gave it to the owner, saying,
'Take good care of him. If it costs any more, put it on my bill.
I'll pay you on my way back.' What do you think?
Which of the three became a neighbor to the man attacked by the robbers?"
"The one who treated him kindly," the religious leader said.
Jesus said, "Go and do the same."
Thank you.
Thank you very much. Got a question from Camilla Belich.
Thank you. Thanks for your articulate submission, and also for the work that you
do in your community.
Pardon me. I liked
your description of a kind of a compassionate response.
And I've seen some of the
evidence-based suggestions you've put in your paper as an
alternative, and I just wanted to check that.
In your view, would that be a more compassionate response than what's proposed
here? Or anything else to add on, on what
you would like to see happen?
Yes, absolutely. I think
those are the particular services and supports that are needed.
There's also the mechanical piece in the middle about how to actually connect
people with those services as well.
So that would be the additional part, how those interactions are made.
I think I'd add one more bit, which is I think people are healed
primarily by community. And I think the
unintentional side effect of this whole idea is it's
actually
dismantled the community by the way it's been gone about.
So I think the actual process of this is actually causing harm,
and therefore diminishing the chance of people's health and well-being because the
community's been diminished.
And we've got a question from Rita Nakay.
On Sunday night, someone was walking into Manukau Woolworths
and they saw a person begging out the front, and they decided to buy from
Baker's Delight both a sweet loaf for them, and they asked them if they like
Marmite because they also bought them scrolls of cheese and Marmite.
Do you think they were an MP, a gang member, or
I don't know what the third person is that you said.
So a lot of us do this kind work without putting pictures on
Facebook. But I just would ask you, please, when you're talking to the people in
your community that are very distressed by this, please
remind them that this isn't criminalizing homelessness, which with
our minister for mental health and everything else we're doing, we're really trying
to tackle those real issues. But this is criminalizing
someone that refuses to follow an order for 24 hours.
Thank you.
Fantastic.
Thank you both for your submission and for joining us this evening as well.
Thank you.
Right, our next submitter is Bianca.
She's joining us online. Great.
You know your stuff.
Tena tatou. Can you hear me?
We can, Bianca. Thank you very much for joining us this evening.
We've got you down for 5 minutes. Actually, we've got
you down for 10 minutes. My apologies.
Oh, 10 minutes.
We've read your written submission.
Just leave some time for questions
Okay, thank you very much. I've got a bit of a
different message there. I'm still on my work Zoom
to ban bottom trawling.
But anyway, I'll just start off by
introducing myself. Nō reira, tena tatou.
He uri tēnei o Ngāpuhi nui tonu. Ko Ngāti Kahu ki Whangaroa te
hapu. Ko Bianca Ranson tōku ingoa.
Kia ora. My name is Bianca, and I am with a
community care and self-defense group called Kaiāwhina,
which is based in Tāmaki Makaurau, Auckland.
I just wanted to very quickly start off with some of my
background and connection to rough sleepers, unhoused
whanau, and our street whanau. And that
began between the years of 12 to
18, when I was working in my grandpa's shop every
Saturday, and it was the only Maori-owned store on Queen Street
in the Auckland CBD, and it was called Ranganui Souvenirs, and
I sat with my grandpa every Saturday for six years while I
was at high school. And it taught me a lot, and one of the things that
I have carried through to today is his expression of
aroha and manaakitanga for our rough sleepers,
and the ability to build a connection and a relationship
with many of them that would come into the store, and
would receive support in multiple different ways from my grandpa,
who would understand how our people
became unhoused, and the many
issues that our people were facing around
poverty and displacement.
And so, that essentially taught me that no
matter who you are, every single person has mana, and everybody
has dignity, and that we must uphold that and respect that,
and for those that are struggling, we must show and extend aroha and
manaakitanga to those people. As I mentioned, Kaiāwhina is a
community care and self-defense group here in Tāmaki, and we
are a group of volunteers who provide marshal and medic
services for protests, and we're born out of the Palestine movement.
And while this week marks the 145th consecutive
week on the ground supporting protests for Palestine in the Auckland CBD, we
are also intersectional, and we have been supporting Kickback Make
Change, an organization dedicated to ending youth homelessness.
We have supported their rangatahi with vigils for the young people who have
lost their lives on the street, and we have also supported their
protests and rallies advocating for more resourcing for wraparound
services, for emergency housing,
and permanent public housing to be made available to them.
We also supported them with the big protest that they had against these move-on
orders. We also support workers' unions, trans, takatapa,
and rainbow community, migrants' rights, and the Maori
protest movement. I'm sure that you will be well aware of the
amount of protests that has happened during this term of the current government,
and we have been
very much on the frontline of seeing
many protest actions and supporting rallies, and really
seeing how much has been happening with the punching down on
disabled people, on women with the fair pay, with Maori
and the treaty rights, and on the environment that we depend on for a
livable future. And now, as the ultimate punch down
on the most vulnerable with the move-on orders targeting young people as
young as 14, those experiencing poverty and extreme
hardship, and often coming from
extremely difficult backgrounds.
Kaiāwhina also supports a community kai initiative on K
Road that was started by a group that formed out of
Kaiāwhina, and for the last six months have been feeding up to
200 rough sleepers, unhoused people, and street
whanau every Monday evening,
and they are coming through for a warm, nutritious meal.
And we are seeing young people come through, we're seeing families come
through with young children, we're seeing elderly, and they are
all coming here to receive a kai each week, but they are also
asking for support with multiple other things that are going
on for them and what they're experiencing living on the streets.
And it has been incredibly
obvious and noticeable, just the increase
in rough sleepers and homelessness within the Auckland
CBD, and I have a reasonable amount of
time to be able to
look back on to the time when I was 12 years old, being aware of
our community that are living on the streets right through till today.
But the amount of homelessness that we are seeing appearing within the
Auckland CBD, a place where these rough sleepers come
for a reason, so that they can have a place of some
kind of visibility, of some kind of safety
for them to be finding a place
to not only find somewhere that is potentially
safe to be at night, but also to have access to the
limited amount of services that are available to them.
I want to now talk about manaakitanga
as something that is very central to Te Tiriti o Waitangi.
And also that the majority of the street whanau that we see
coming through for the community kai on Mondays, or
whether it is the street whanau that we are connecting with down in the CBD every
week when we are supporting rallies or protests, making sure that we're checking
in, letting them know if something is going to be passing them by, giving them a
heads up about what's going on, and building that trust and relationship with them
We know that the move on orders have started since settler
colonial violence reached these shores of Aotearoa, and
it forced our people from our whenua, from our kāinga,
from our tūrangawaewae. And this example
of the move on orders is a continual
display of using state violence
in the interests of protecting capital at the expense of the
most vulnerable people in this country.
And I would just like to
mention some of the kōrero that I've heard this evening, which has been--
It's talked about this is the most homelessness that this country has ever seen.
We have seen the multiple attacks on many different fronts, on many vulnerable
communities, and the attacks that are
happening against Te Tiriti o Waitangi.
And what this is doing amongst our communities is that it's
bringing us together, and it's creating a
united front of people who are centered in a commitment to Te
Tiriti justice, in a commitment to aroha and
manaakitanga, and stepping in where the state is failing to.
And so there is an immense amount of power there that is being
built within communities who are getting on and addressing the needs of the
most vulnerable. But we are wanting
to make sure that our taxpayer
money is being spent correctly and
responsibly, and supporting people who
desperately need safe, affordable housing, more
public housing, actually have access to
emergency housing. We're seeing a celebration of, "This is how
many people we have moved out of emergency housing." But the
reality is, is that you have made it so incredibly
difficult for people to even be able to access emergency
housing, let alone have the confidence in the system to
go onto a wait list to potentially enter into
public housing, or any commitment from this government
to build more public housing through Kāinga
Ora, for example. So from our lived experience
and our material reality that we are seeing every single weekend on the
grounds in Auckland, that we are seeing on K Road, where we are feeding up
to 200 people, completely funding this ourselves
out of people's aroha and care, and need to step in to support
these people. We want to make it very clear that this is a
continual act of violence. It is state violence
against those that are most vulnerable, and that you have a
responsibility to think about how
to provide the resourcing, to provide the
services that can be available to these people, to help
them move into a situation of meeting the basic
necessities of life. Which is food,
healthcare, and a warm, dry home, so that they can
then start to heal some of that trauma,
heal some of what the experience of what they've been through, and then
come into becoming part of our wider communities in a
way that they deserve, in a way that their mana and their
dignity is respected and honored as should
be for everybody in Aotearoa, and is actually guaranteed
for everybody in this country under Te Tiriti
o Waitangi. So all of this is connected, the attacks against
Te Tiriti, the attacks against the vulnerable,
and we say that the
move on orders must be completely abandoned
and thrown away in its entirety. Nō reira, tēnā tātou
katoa.
Thanks, Bianca, and thank you very much for your written submission and for
presenting to us this evening as well. Thank you very much.
Can members come to our next submitter, which is Liz, who's going to be joining us
online.
Oh.
Hi, Liz.
Hi. Kia ora.
We just can't see you at the moment, but we can hear you.
Mm.
And that's quite all right.
Yep.
We have you down for five minutes. We have read your written
submission. Just leave some time for questions. Over to you.
Yep, sure.
Yep.
Okay, I'm trying to start my video. Sorry about that.
That's okay.
I think I had.
Okay, good. I'm doing this off my phone.
Yeah, pōmare, and thanks for this chance to be here.
And I'd like to endorse the words of the previous speaker, Bianca
Ransom, both words and actions. Really grateful, yeah, in listening
to what Bianca had to say. I want to make three quick points tonight.
I think affordable housing is essential.
I note that the Police Association is opposed to this legislation and
proposed legislation, and that I see decent housing as
climate adaptation.
Mm. Let's say that I think affordable housing is essential.
Half of New Zealanders who are homeless are under 25, and
half are female. Somebody living on the street, despite the cold, the discomfort,
and the dangers, is there because this is their least worst option.
We need to have affordable housing so all of us can live somewhere safe and
healthy. Some of our young people need safe alternatives.
I think parents with dependent children need decent housing so they can leave
unsafe relationships. Mm. And we know that
housing is way too expensive, particularly rental housing, and
yeah, and that-
Yeah. Because some people, very few, not having the
alternatives. We also know that through the Royal Commission on Abuse and Care that
too many New Zealanders have had horrific childhoods.
We know that one in four females and one in seven males are sexually abused by
adulthood, and that about 1% of offenders are convicted, so the rest go
on to continue to offend. And that we know that one in 10 of us are affected by the
disease of alcoholism, and that means the family around them.
So there are all sorts of reasons why a family may not be a safe
place to be, and why somebody is
forced onto the streets, and health issues and so on.
Yeah, and the sheer expense of housing.
Personally,
my partner and I have been lucky to be comfortably off, got to that stage of being
retired.
We would have happily paid much more taxes to make sure that
there was decent housing in this country. Social housing is a good thing.
My mother-in-law was able to be in a state house in the back of Dunedin
about 50 years ago when her marriage broke up with her young family.
Yeah, and also note that the Police Association are opposed.
They don't want to criminalize victims of poverty and
ill health. And
that it's way more expensive to actually put people in prison than
to create housing.
And also, I wonder what effect this will have on the morale and retention of police
officers who are forced to deal with what are social justice issues,
and criminalize people. There is already the legislation to deal with
criminal activity.
And,
hmm, and I've seen the rise of homelessness in Newtown and Wellington, where we
were living.
Yeah. It's
awful. Last point is extreme weather events that we're
experiencing, which best case scenario will intensify over the next
20, 30 years thanks to the emissions we've already overheated the world
with. These events act as a stress multiplier,
so those of us who are already on the edges of survival are most at risk.
Decent, safe housing and other supports for people currently homeless
is actually a really important climate adaptation
policy. Yeah, so in closing, please
put your focus on decent housing and consider all the
different experiences that people have that lead them to a situation where
living on the street is the safest option. Yeah.
I don't want to be this country. Yeah.
Yeah. Thank you. Thanks so
much.
Thank you, Liz. Thank you very much.
Doesn't appear to be any questions for you, so we're really grateful for the
written submission you made and also for the oral submission you've just done as
well.
Yep.
Thank you very much for your time.
Thanks, Liz. Thanks, Liz. Ka pai. Thank you.
Bye-bye.
Okay. Our next submitter is Challenge 2000 Trust.
We've got Stephen who's going to be joining us.
Good evening, all.
And just introduce us to your colleague.
Most definitely. So it's great to have you all here, I must say.
I admire everyone that can spend all this time after hours doing some
wonderful work for our country. Thank you.
So I'm Steve O'Connor. This is Father Eddie Conroy.
He is our chaplain, and he's also worked at Challenge for the last 40
years as a counselor and support person for young people.
Interestingly enough, as I walk up the steps here, I got a text from a young person
who's just been thrown out of a house and presently living on the
street somewhere in Wellington as we speak.
So after this, I'll be putting my jeans on.
Might take you to home first, and we will go and see if we can support this young
person. So potentially, this is a young person presently living on our streets who
may be subject to this
law, should it become one.
So I do thank you for the opportunity to appear today.
So Steve O'Connor,
appearing on behalf of Challenge 2000.
We're a Wellington youth development organization that's worked alongside
vulnerable children since 1988.
So we've been around for a long time.
For almost four decades, we have supported young people who have experienced abuse,
neglect, former state care,
homelessness,
mental health challenges, and involvement in the youth justice system.
As you know from reading my submission or our submission, I oppose this bill.
Challenge 2000 oppose this bill.
We oppose it because we do not believe the additional powers proposed are
necessary
or likely to produce lasting improvements in community safety.
We strongly support victims of crime,
strongly support the New Zealand Police, and safe public
spaces.
We also support caring for vulnerable young people and adults.
Our concern is that this bill
focuses primarily on moving vulnerable people
rather than addressing the circumstances that have actually
precipitated them being on the street in a vulnerable
situation in the first place.
To give you a bit of a background and just understand why I'm here
and why I'm speaking to you,
I'd just note that I began my career as a social worker when I was in my
early years,
before serving 23 years of the New Zealand Police.
I ended up as a senior police officer,
but I spent most of my career supporting young people.
I was both youth aid officer and youth development officer, and I was the
officer in charge of community and youth services in Lower Hutt for something
like 10 to 15 years.
I now work as a senior social worker supporting care experience young
people through our transitions to adulthood program.
When I first joined Challenge, I was the CEO and decided that perhaps
front line is a bit more my thing.
So I thought I'd better fess up
As opposed to wear my tree-hugging social work suit, just in case
you didn't get the message that I'm actually a person who comes to this from a
past experience of on the street supporting young people.
So across both those professions, social work and police, I've worked with similar
children, similar young people, similar families and communities.
Now, why do we oppose the bill?
In our view, the safest communities are created when police are supported
by strong care and protection systems,
effective social work, and trusted community partnerships.
The question is not whether harmful behavior should be addressed.
Of course it should.
The question is whether this bill provides the right response.
Challenge 2000's experience tells us and guides us,
my policing experience tells me and guides me, that this bill does
not provide the right response.
A move on direction may move someone from one place to another,
but as you would all obviously understand, it does not provide
housing, treat trauma,
reconnect the young person, or anyone else for that matter, to education, restore
family relationships, provide addiction or mental health support,
assign a social worker. It simply moves the problem.
Many of the young people that I have supported over my lifetime career
have experienced abuse, neglect, family
violence, unstable housing, repeated loss of trusted relationships.
When these needs remain unmet,
offending often becomes a symptom of a deeper trauma.
So what do we believe works? The most effective police
officers build strong relationships with schools, iwi, social workers, youth
workers, and community organizations such as ours.
Police can identify care and protection concerns.
For example, they make reports of concerns.
They can use alternative action where appropriate.
They can work alongside Oranga Tamariki, community organizations,
before offending becomes entrenched.
These pathways, we believe, should be strengthened and properly
resourced.
Greater attention should be also given to care experienced
young people, specifically aged 14 to 17,
which is covered, both the age group, 14-year-olds plus, is covered by this
act or this bill, I should say.
And practical support should be extended to older care
experienced young adults aged 18 to 25, or
those adults 18 to 20 can
be subject to youth court extended care orders
because they have such high needs.
So Challenge 2000 respectfully asks the committee not
to recommend that this bill proceeds.
What we do recommend is strengthening the police
by strengthening the systems that support them,
investing in earlier care and protection responses,
increasing social work support to vulnerable groups, particularly young
people under the age of 18, but also 18 to
20 if they're under a court order. Improving access to
supported accommodation,
and continuing to invest in trusted community organizations.
Both policing and social work exist to protect children, support
victims, strengthen families, and build safer communities.
As I've already said, moving vulnerable people from
one place to another may actually make the problem less visible.
However, it does not make the problem disappear.
The last point I make is one of the perhaps unintended consequences of
this bill
is that
you might make it harder for the police.
Because if they start arresting young people because they won't
give them their name and address as this bill allows, they're going
to find themselves in conflict with Section 214 of the Children, Young Persons and
Their Families Act, Oranga Tamariki Act.
And they're going to find themselves being in youth court trying to
justify an illegal arrest,
which isn't much fun for a cop, let me tell you.
And I have
many examples where that happens already.
It can cost $10,000 a time easily that the police have to fork out,
plus you destroy the confidence of the police officer.
So that's an unintended consequence, and I suggest you've got to look very closely
at the conflict that you're raising in this bill.
So I thank you for this opportunity to appear today, and I welcome any questions
that you have.
Thanks, Stephen, and thanks, Eddie. Let's see.
We've got a question from Camilla Belich.
Thanks for your submission and for the work that you do.
We've heard it, I think, from another submitter, and I think it's a really
interesting point what you raise around trust and policing.
Yes.
What do you think the impact of this bill would
be on the police officer and their ability to
police with trust?
If they don't get the support,
the training,
and the
motivation to use the care and protection provisions of the act as a priority
to vulnerable young people, there are lots...
They can actually use Section 48 under the act to uplift a young
person who is vulnerable and at risk, and they can do that in a
caring, sharing way, but they have to then take the young person to an OT or social
worker. Now, if they are resourced enough to manage that
in a good way, we pay all this money out to lock people up in prisons,
but where are all the Oranga Tamariki
houses, support places that social workers can take kids who are
vulnerable
until something can be found for them, until some of their needs can be met?
So I think if that happened, the risk is
you're going to destroy police officers'
ability to build those trusting relationships. I'm talking about the street cops.
Okay, it already occurs in the specialist services, youth services, and such like
that.
But this potentially has the
risk of destroying,
eating away at that trust with young people.
Remembering that those young people on the streets who are highly vulnerable,
potentially are on the pipeline into adult recidivist offending.
That's what we have to stop.
If you make that worse, that destroy that trust, all that's going to happen is that
you're going to just speed that process up
as opposed to put in place care and protection
preventative measures of which the police
are the front of that.
So it's a huge risk this act, this bill could-
Okay, and we've got one quick question from Rima Nayak.
Just a quick one. Thank you very much for being here.
In your experience, what would you say is one or two of the main reasons why we
find children under the age of 18 on the streets?
Adverse
experiences.
At home.
Causing trauma. Well, not necessarily.
It could be-- In fact, a lot of the young people I'm supporting now, which I do 30
young people, care experienced.
Most of the abuse that they have suffered is that has been in care by
caregivers. So in other words, the state has a part to play in
the reason why they're on the street in the first place, and why they therefore
will be subject to the provisions of this bill.
Okay. Thank you.
Thank you very much. Thanks, Steven, and thank you, Eddie, for both being here
today.
Thank you.
Thanks very much. Really appreciate it. Keep it going.
Okay, our next submitter is the Karangahape Road Business
Association, and we've got Jamie who's going to be joining us.
Gidday, Jamie. Thank you very much for joining us and for being with us this
evening. We've read your written submission.
We've got you down for 10 minutes, if you can just leave some time for questions,
please. But over to you.
Sure. Can you hear me?
We can.
Great.
Well,
taking the submission as read,
if there are any questions on that, please feel free to jump in at any time.
But
I'm speaking on behalf of my membership, which is
approximately 600 businesses who are represented
by
a board that is elected every year.
And my board have asked that I submit
from our point of view. I think a lot of
what happens with the move on orders and the impetus
for move on orders seems to be
done in the name of business and being done in the name of
business associations and reducing disruption to trading.
I think
we experience a lot of
rough sleeping and unhoused
street whānau, and also housed street whānau with
a lot of social problems on Karangahape Road.
But it is the view of my membership and my board that the move on
orders are a mistake and that they are a
lost opportunity to
come up with proper solutions to...
These are real
problems, but we specifically ask that
sleeping be removed from
the proposed legislation because there
are no
situations in which people sleeping
are threatening people. And we're dealing with
street whānau on a day-to-day basis.
It's when the behavior is antisocial that those
issues get stressful for people trying
to operate businesses. And
we think that there are a bunch
of responses to these issues that we've been
repeatedly asking for and not being heard on, and instead we're
getting this non-response which is going to
make things worse and waste resources.
Great. Okay, Jamie, we've got a question from Tamatha Paul.
Kia ora, Jamie.
Thank you for making this submission.
And it is really helpful because you're right, they really are
framing this as something that they're doing for you and particularly in Auckland.
So it is really helpful to have you bringing the voices of
businesses on K Road here.
I'd really love to hear from you what things you're seeing on K Road
that you think are working,
in terms of any community or even maybe government funded
initiatives that you can see that might be having a positive
impact towards reducing homelessness.
Yeah. I spend a lot of the time on the street on Karangahape
Road and throughout the CBD.
The things that I see working
are
the very well designed, well-resourced,
and
most fundamentally well staffed housing
provided on Grey's Ave, which is just outside our area.
A facility called Te Matawai, which is purpose-built.
I see the resourced third spaces
for street whānau and for peop-- like a lot of people who are
housed in
social housing or of limited means and
with addiction issues and things like that, are housed in quite
small apartments that aren't really
They don't really function as social spaces, so a lot of the socializing happens on
the street. So the Lifewise Merge Cafe on
Karangahape Road is incredibly invaluable in terms of
providing a third space for
people to see their peers and to get support and those sorts of
things. Lifewise do an amazing
job. The Auckland City Mission do an amazing job.
I can't remember the name of the program, but just recently council have started
funding sort of a daytime program of activities.
I think
there's a need for maybe five or six
different third spaces within, say, the Auckland CBD,
and at the moment there's maybe one or two.
I think
if these issues are shared around a bit more, instead of being
herded into one place,
that's when you tend to see things improve.
Mm-hmm.
You asked me what else is working well.
Yeah, there's a hell of a lot of good stuff working well.
I think the Kickback
program that happens on Karangahape Road is well worth a
mention.
Yeah. That's probably all that comes to mind.
That's awesome. Thank you.
And we've got a question from Dan Rosemore.
Thanks, Chair.
Thanks for that submission. Now, the government has often justified
this bill on the basis that business and city centers need
additional tools to respond to antisocial behavior.
And as a business association, I find it interesting that you have concluded that
rough sleeping should not be included in the move on powers.
And I was just wondering, why is that, and why have your members
taken that position?
I think that
it's not
wanting police to not be able to respond to
antisocial behavior. And I think
the toleration of intimidation, the toleration of
violence, the breach of liquor bans,
all of those things need to be
policed better.
We want
more action, not less action on those things.
It's just removing the sleeping because it
just puts everything out of kilter
in terms of those relationships between the police and
the people on the street, and the social workers.
By including sleeping in the legislation, we are just going to
move people from sleeping visibly to sleeping
invisibly. So they're going to move from Karangahape Road in front of
Samoan House to the laneway in behind Samoan House,
where they're less visible and in more
danger themselves and are more danger to other people.
I think we've got a problem. We're better to keep it out in the open.
When people are sleeping, they're lying down, they're prone, they're not standing
over anybody.
I've never seen someone sleeping
being aggressive while sleeping.
And I've
effectively moved on people who are rough sleeping many times
personally and through the security that we employ seven
days a week. So
it just
seems crazy to have that
act of sleeping on the sidewalk to be
included in this,
if that makes sense.
No, thank you.
Fantastic. Well, thank you, Jamie.
Really appreciate you joining us this evening and for your written submission as
well. So thank you for your time.
Cheers.
Okay. We've got Amanda, who's going to be presenting to us.
On Zoom. Great.
Hi, Amanda. Thank you very much for joining us this evening.
We've read your written submission. We've got you down for five minutes.
Just leave a little bit of time for questions.
Kia ora. Kia ora tātou. Tēnā te mihi kia kotou.
E te pō nei.
So thank you for the chance to submit.
It's been really fascinating and heartening to hear the submitters
that have been just prior to me,
and hear people expressing a generalized concern about this
proposed bill. I guess the things that I want to focus in are
about one of the bill's purposes to address
the public sense of safety and who is meant by the
public.
So in my job, I'm a senior lecturer in environmental studies at Te Herenga
Waka Victoria University in environmental studies, and my PhD is in
geography. And really at the heart of my PhD
in geography is considerations of public space and who
gets to access spaces of democracy, and how and why.
So, when this issue of a public sense of safety
is raised, it makes me wonder whose safety and at whose expense.
So I think about the 14-year-olds who could be caught up in this bill
and the implications for their lifelong safety and security of being
criminalized for failing to obey a move on order if they have nowhere else to
move on to.
And I was also reflecting on the fact that England and Wales just last
month have repealed their Vagrancy Act, their 200-year-old act
that criminalized rough sleeping.
And I think it's probably not a great indication that we're following in the
footsteps of England and Wales 200 years ago and testing out something
that there's already a large body of evidence that indicates that that is
not a good way to treat rough sleepers.
So Christopher Roberts, a legal academic, writes about how the Vagrancy Act
there has stigmatized the poor, and the use of police discretion
in that law has led to the arbitrary detention of many poor people.
And the way that it has targeted working class beneficiaries and
those who are out of work. An article from
last year by Okara- Surprising no one says that the
criminalization of rough sleeping and poverty does nothing to address the
root causes of homelessness. So it's in spite of a whole
enormous body of evidence pointing to the dangers and the risks and
the cost to poor people of this kind of legislation that this is being
proposed.
I was pleased to see that there was a carve-out for protest, that protest wouldn't
be included in the move on orders. But I think it's a slippery slope
when it does capture activities
indicating an intent to inhabit a public place.
So we talk about that as preemptive policing and preemptive
criminalization, where it's based on a supposed intent,
when the action hasn't actually been carried out yet.
And I can see how that would be very much a slippery slope in relation to
activism that often involves occupying public places.
So great to see the protest exclusion.
I would really strongly advocate that the whole thing be withdrawn,
but that intent
aspect of it
raises massive red flags for how the police are supposed to
understand and predict intent.
So I guess I'm speaking in that capacity as an
academic who has access to research about this stuff, but also as a resident
of Strathmore Park here in Wellington.
In our community, almost 80 public housing
homes that are proposed in a redevelopment of existing state housing have been
canceled by this government. So if I look out my window just over on the hill
there, there are multiple boarded-up buildings that could
be redeveloped. Whole streets of public housing that are
waiting for families in a community that really wants people living in our
community. We want people in our public housing. We want public housing here.
We know that it enriches our community and brings enormous diversity to our
community, and yet we have no answer for Ngati Apa Street
and what kind of development is happening there despite repeated attempts to get
that information from Kainga Ora. So move on to where?
We've got whole communities desperately wanting to home and house and
support people, but unless that public housing exists, there's nowhere for
them to go. So we just end up in the criminalization of poor
people with no options out of that. Kia ora koutou.
Fantastic. Thanks, Amanda.
Doesn't look like there's any questions from members, so we're really grateful for
you submitting to us this evening. So thank you very much for your time.
Na mahe.
Fantastic. Our next submitter is Hugh, who I believe is going to join us in
person. Come on up.
Thanks, Hugh. We've got you down for 10 minutes.
We have read your written submission, but please just leave some time for
questions. Over to you.
Kia ora. Thank you, Chair, members of the committee.
My name is Hugh Laracy McChrystal, and I appear for Manatahu Limited, a Maori-led
health and disability research consultancy.
Our position is straightforward.
We ask the committee to report this bill back with the recommendation that it not
proceed. If it does proceed, three changes are essential.
Remove the begging on rough sleeping grounds, constrain the new
power to detain a person for their details, and write in an explicit
disability safeguard.
A, this bill criminalizes status, not conduct.
This bill criminalizes the visible effects of poverty and disability, not
harmful conduct. Genuine disorder, threatening someone or blocking a doorway
is already an offense, and we back enforcing it.
What grounds E and F add is a power to move a person on
for begging or rough sleeping. That is a status, not an act.
Begging has not been a crime here since 1981.
This bill revives a control Parliament chose to abandon.
And unlike every existing identity power which requires a suspected offense,
the new Section 8C lets police detain a person who has done nothing
criminal. It is why the Attorney General
reported to Parliament on the 14th of May 2026 that the bill is
inconsistent with the Bill of Rights on freedom of expression and freedom of
movement.
B, on the government's own evidence, it will not work.
The Ministry of Justice's own regulatory impact statement found a lack of
empirical evidence that these orders reduce offending.
It modeled that they would add between 200 and 800 court cases and
about six more prisoners a year at roughly
$120,000 each, and it called the penalties
disproportionately high. New Zealand Police advise that they already have
the tools that they need and that enforcement is not the way to deal with
homelessness or poverty. Ministry officials predicted the most likely
effect is simply to move people from one place to the next and named disabled
people and people in mental distress as most at risk.
Moving people on does not make a street safer.
It displaces the problem and spends public money doing it.
C, this bill will cause harm, especially to disabled people.
A study in the Journal of the American Medical Association by Borokers and
colleagues modeling 23 United States cities found that
continually moving people on would cause hundreds to over 2,000 additional overdose
deaths for every 10,000 people over a decade by cutting them
off from medication and care.
The triggers of this bill being disorderly, disruptive, intimidating are
undefined, and disabilities routinely misread as exactly those things.
That is the finding of the police's own commission research.
The Donald Beasley Institute's 2024 report, which records autistic and deaf
people and people with brain injuries being read as suspicious or intoxicated.
Nearly two-thirds of people in prison have a history of head injury.
The Section 8C power to detain and to fine a person $500 for
not answering fast enough from age 14 will fall hardest on those who cannot
comply.
Do you think a 14-year-old who is on the street wants to be there?
Do you think they want to sleep on the street?
Do you think they want to have everyone watch them as they're trying to do the most
basic thing that every human has to do? Nobody wants to be on the street.
Nobody likes the fact that they're there.
They sleep there because that's the safest place for them
They have no other option, and often the homes that they go to would be more safe
than where they have to sleep.
Point D, it damages the police's reputation and falls hardest on Maori.
Public cooperation with police depends on their being seen as fair.
The procedural justice research is clear that fairness is what makes communities
report crime and call for help. Turn officers on people whose only
visible fact is poverty, and you erode that trust.
It is necessary for those most at risk, who are the people forced to live on our
streets, to trust our police and not live in fear of persecution at their
hands.
The burden this bill creates is not shared evenly.
Papaitā Hauora finds that Maori, one in six New Zealanders, are
nearly a third of those in severe housing deprivation, and EHE
research finds four in five homeless women are wahine Maori.
The United Nations Disability Committee found Maori disabled people three
times as likely to live in poverty.
A power aimed at rough sleeping falls on Maori and on disabled Maori most
of all. The Waitangi Tribunal's Hauora inquiry is clear.
Where harm is this uneven, the Crown's duty is active protection.
What works? So what would we support?
We support the response that evidence backs.
Housing First cut long-term homelessness in Finland by about two-thirds,
and Canada's At Home/CHEZ SOI randomized trial paid
for roughly two-thirds of itself through fewer hospital, emergency, and
cell nights. It works here, too. Measured against the
government's own linked data, New Zealand Housing First tenants had 44%
fewer hospitalizations, 43% fewer criminal charges,
and 38% higher income five years on.
And a tenancy costs about $4,800 a year against
$56,000 for emergency housing. Britain repealed its
200-year-old begging law this year.
New Zealand would be adding grounds our peers have just removed.
Genuine disorder is already illegal, and we back enforcing it.
This bill adds nothing for public safety.
Seeing police forcefully remove the disadvantaged, incapacitated
homeless from our streets will not make this country safer or more
appealing. This bill represents our country moving backwards while international
partners move forwards. To reiterate, this bill criminalizes
poverty and disability. The Attorney General says it breaches the Bill of
Rights. The police say it will not work, and it falls hardest on disabled people
and on Maori. The evidence points to solutions based on providing useful
support through a home and care, not to a fine.
Tēnā koutou katoa. I welcome your questions.
Fantastic. Thank you very much, Hugh.
I'm just looking to see if any members have questions for you.
Thanks.
A question from Rima Naklay.
Yeah. Hi, thanks, Hugh. So Hugh, what brought you to the organization
that you represent?
Um-
Are you part of the founding... I haven't looked into it.
No, I'm not at all, actually. My friend recently worked for the director of our
company, who is disabled himself, and I saw it as an
opportunity mainly because it was better than the hospitality work I was doing
before. But when I came to this company, I didn't really know much about disabled
rights or just the amount of difficulty these people face.
But it's very interesting when you go to restaurants that you go to as a normal
person, you realize with them, when you go with them, how much difficult it is to
just do basic things.
Mm-hmm.
The people on our streets especially are disabled, and the fact that they
cannot even find a nice place to sleep.
The reason that I find this company is very helpful for me is that I now get to see
the world through a lens that I feel like people, especially people around this
table right now, who come from most likely higher income households,
good backgrounds, and now live in stable housing, won't have to experience-
I had a very difficult background, by the way, anyway. Yeah.
Sorry. Just a general assumption of the majority of the committee.
I'll let you stay there.
I'll get Jeremy. Yeah, yeah.
Yeah. Okay, so just supplementary if I can, thank you for explaining that,
and good on you for the work that you're doing.
You're talking about seeing things through a certain lens, and of course,
probably no one has it as hard as someone on the street right now.
Mm-hmm.
But I listen to, in South Auckland where I represent, a
lot of business owners that say they're losing people
because they're trying to raise their family and pay their mortgages.
And these are real stories, not I'm just making them up.
Mm-hmm.
Because there's a lot of people that will be outside their shops, either rough
sleeping or begging,
patrons say, "Look, we want to support you, but we just don't feel comfortable
having to go through that." I'm okay with it, but others don't feel comfortable.
And all this is, is telling people to move
on for 24 hours where there seems to be a problem.
Mm-hmm.
What about the lens of those people that are trying to raise their family and
work?
I understand it's a difficult situation, and that it definitely is hard for
businesses, especially when they're trying to provide a good hospitality
experience and difficulty keeping a customer base when they have people around the
entrances or potentially-
Who pay their mortgage.
Yeah, who pay their mortgage. And I definitely agree with them and that they are
victims of this, but I would also point to the fact that the government has reduced
a lot of emergency housing.
Mm-hmm.
It has created a problem in which now the people who would normally be in
situations in which they could get out of this have no way to do this.
Yeah.
I see this as a cyclical thing. These people will move a street over and then come
back, and then 24 hours, as you said.
I see it also enraging them against police.
Mm-hmm.
These people often have little hope.
I expect that when the police move them on, and probably have to do so
forcefully because these people may be on drugs, or they may be so tired and
upset with how these things are going that they have to just, I don't know,
speak back to police, that I feel that this will then create more unrest and make
these people less likely to comply and reduce the hope that they already don't
have.
Mm-hmm. Okay.
Thank you. And we've got a question from Carl Bates.
Mm-hmm.
Thanks, Chair.
I could stand corrected, but would it surprise you if I said to you
that there hasn't been a single person who's come to my
office in Whanganui with a challenge either around
emergency housing or housing that hasn't been able
to get help and get into the housing that they needed?
Oh.
Would that surprise you?
Well, yeah, the stats are totally-
Well, I'm not asking you.
Stats totally-
No.
Thank you.
That's up to you.
I would say that that's very fortunate.
I'd say that's not the case for a majority of these people.
I'd also say that there's a-
That's the narrative that's being- Not many organised criminals
It's not a major city.
Okay.
It just means nothing.
To answer your question, that would surprise me. I would be surprised by that.
Okay. Thank you.
I feel like a lot of people struggle.
Can I ask a question?
Yeah. But yeah, questions come to me.
Would it surprise you if every week in Christchurch Central, I have people
coming into the office seeking accommodation who can't get it,
notwithstanding that they're sick or they've got kids?
That would not surprise me at all.
No, I didn't think it would. Thank you. Thank you for your work.
Yeah. Thank you.
If I could end quick. Would you?
You did a fantastic job. So thank you very much for joining us this evening and for
your submission.
Thank you.
Okay, members, our next submitter is New Zealand Young
Labour.
Oh.
That'll be why.
Nice.
Me.
G'day.
Thank you for that. Help come.
Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you for joining us this evening. We've read your written submission.
We've got you down for 10 minutes. Just leave some time for questions at the end.
Over to you.
Kia ora. Thank you, Mr. Chair. Thank you everyone for having me.
My name is Samita Singh and I'm the regional vice president of Young
Labour. I'm here on behalf of the organization to speak to this bill and
to urge the select committee to oppose the bill in its current
form. And I take my written submission as being read.
Today, I will speak to you on three limbs that, in our view, show why this bill is
not fit for purpose. The first being how this bill
inherently criminalizes homelessness and the harm that comes with
it. The second being how this bill adds unnecessary strain
on already limited police and court resources.
The third being the need for wraparound support services to aid those who are
sleeping rough.
The Move on Orders Bill is being framed as providing the police with alternative
powers to move people on when they're displaying disorderly, intimidating, or
disruptive behavior.
On its face, that might sound like a reasonable public order tool.
But in reality, this bill would inherently criminalize rough sleepers because it
targets people being in a public place and exercising their freedom of movement,
as defined in our Bill of Rights Act.
It is not addressing violent offending, but rather it's addressing
visible poverty.
This is a breach of New Zealand's Bill of Rights Act, which is also noted in the
Attorney General's report, which was given to this select committee.
It is clear that this bill has been introduced to criminalize homelessness and to
further push vulnerable groups into a criminal justice cycle, which is never
ending for many people. When the state begins to penalize
the simple act of existing in a public space whilst homeless,
it steps away from a rights respecting framework and towards a model where
deprivation itself is treated as a form of disorder.
The move on orders would allow the police to impose unrealistic financial
penalties that vulnerable groups would simply not be able to afford.
For someone sleeping on Lambton Quay with no income and no savings, a fine
is not an incentive. It is an impossible
debt.
Or in the alternative, this bill states that an individual could be liable to
imprisonment for a term not exceeding three months.
This demonstrates that criminalization of homelessness and the strain of
limited police and court resources are inherently linked.
If police officers are exercising their unchecked discretion to issue
infringements or charging individuals for breaching a move on order, the
courts will be strained in juggling their workload.
Every infringement and every charge for breaching a move on order is yet
another file on a police officer's desk and another matter before the
courts, a court system which is already overworked and at
a bursting seams point.
Criminalizing homelessness sends a message from the state that poverty and housing
insecurity are problems to be moved on rather than being addressed through the
adequate channels.
It says that the problem is that people can be seen, not that they have nowhere
safe to go.
Housing insecurity and poverty simply cannot be resolved through introducing a
bill like this. You cannot legislate homelessness
away by creating a new offense. It is important that this
issue is addressed at its heart,
by looking honestly at the support services that are accessible to these
vulnerable groups and identifying what needs to be strengthened.
It is our belief that stronger social housing, financial support,
mental health services, and counseling would provide a strong foundation.
By having these readily accessible, individuals and groups would be able to
reach out to access the support that they need in order to support them into safer
living conditions where they have a roof over their head and running water to
use.
Many rough sleepers choose to remain within public places such as Lambton Quay for
safety. The safety of lighting, safety through the
constant presence of people, and the safety of public surveillance.
Those are rational choices in an environment where other options may
feel more dangerous,
whether that's an unsafe home,
overcrowded shelters, or a secluded area where no one is watching
and they are unsure of what will happen to them in the night.
Without any support from people or state funded institution, rough sleepers are
further isolated and are going through the criminal justice
cycle at a crazy rate.
They are not choosing to sleep on the street for the thrill of it, but rather they
are pushed out of society, often by factors beyond their
control. In our view, it is clear that there are
two options on this table for this committee today.
To criminalize homelessness
or to invest in real solutions. We urge this
committee to invest in real solutions. Thank you, Mr. Chair.
Thanks, Samita. We've got a question from Camilla Belich.
Thanks very much for your submission.
Just because you're coming from the perspective of younger people-
Yeah
... what would you like to see young people, especially those who are struggling,
and how would you like to see them treated?
What's kind of one thing that you would like to see happen that would improve the
situation for young people in this situation?
I think the big thing for us is wraparound support.
I come from Gisborne where we have quite a high population of homelessness,
including quite recently a high percentage of youth, as young as
about 14, 15. So if they had the support services To
be able to access and reach out. They could be put in a situation where they're
not living on the street, that they've got shelter, and that they've got access to
the mental support systems to make sure that, because they might be in a situation
where it's unsafe to be at home, through no fault of their own, they're able to
reach out and get that support.
Yeah, great. Thank you.
Fantastic. And a question from Rima Nak.
Tatika, Sumita.
Tatika.
Thanks for traveling from
Gisborne.
So I take it you've read the bill?
Yes.
So where in the bill are we criminalizing homelessness?
If you turn to ... If you give me one moment, I've got the bill with me here.
So specifically, if you turn to Section 8F of the proposed
bill,
and then you look at the breach of what a move on order is.
And one of the things that ticks off the police being able to issue a move on order
is displaying homelessness and the activity of setting up camp or sitting at the
house. Which someone that has a home wouldn't be doing on the street.
And if you think about it rationally, a lot of these individuals won't be
in the right state of mind to follow a move on order and to move out of the
area for the 24 hours. So there's a high chance that they're going to be
breaching the move on order and will be subject to either a fine of up to, I think
it's $2,000 or imprisonment, depending on the situation.
So if you think about it logically, in the flow and effect, it's criminalizing
homelessness in that sense.
Great answer.
It's not technically-
Okay. You're not the only one who thinks that
... criminalizing everybody sitting down.
Sorry, if I can just, Mr. Chair.
Yeah.
So we're not criminalizing homelessness-
Picking up the hole
... where it's an offense to breach a move on order.
Say it as much as you want, doesn't make it true.
Yeah.
It is true.
Nick.
Sorry.
It's great.
I've got the right law.
Back in your box.
Peter.
Oh, hey.
Come on. Come on, Khalid.
Peter.
They've answered for you, Sumita.
I was going to say, I could see why you would think that, but as someone that's
studying law and politics and comes from a small town, if you think about it
logically in the flow of effect, and
as legislators, you should know the implications of what it looks like at face
value when you're going through court.
So as someone studying law, you would know it's what's written down here.
It's not
what we just kind of want to think it is.
Thank you.
She gave you a great answer.
Thank you, Duncan.
Carl Bates.
Uh, the supplementary's been asked, Chair.
Okay. Sumita, thank you very much for joining us this evening and for your
submission as well. All right?
Thank you. Thank you very much.
Thank you.
That was awesome. Thank you.
Thank you. Great.
Members, I just will remind you that, um, questions come through me.
Um,
obviously we want the questions to be aligned with the piece of legislation that
the person is submitting on. Um, and, uh, try to
avoid any unnecessary comments that are
responsive. Okay. We're going to be joined by Erin, who's joining us on
Zoom. Thank you, Erin, for joining us, and thank you for your written submission as
well. We've got you down for five minutes.
Okay.
Um, and if you can just leave some time at the end for questions.
Yeah.
Over to you, Erin.
Uh, tena koutou. Um, my name's Erin.
I'm a student in my final semester of undergrad at
Waikato University. Um, and as part of my study, I have done
some study in computer science, particularly in cybersecurity-
Nice
... and in the social sciences, um, relevant to this,
uh, through, uh, sociology and social policy and criminology.
Um, I want to say clearly from the outset that I do not
support the Summary Offences, uh, Summary Offences Move
on Orders Amendment Bill, and recommend that it not progress any
further. Um, I'll take my submission as read,
and I would like to expand on the issues as I see it
in regard to this legislation from a critical
criminological and security perspective.
Um, so I see this,
uh, this bill as part of a larger pattern of securitization, where we're
turning what are not security issues into security issues.
Um, what I mean by that is that, uh,
homelessness is primarily a social and
a, uh, public health issue as I see it.
But the way that this bill is written, we're treating it like people being
homeless, people rough sleeping, as a threat to public security, which I would
say it is not.
Um, I think it's also an example of security theater.
Um,
even in the regulatory impact statement and the policy statement
attached to this bill, we do not, we do not define a
true security or public safety concern.
So we shouldn't treat it as one.
I, I think that when we say sense of safety, that's not the same as
there being an actual safety issue.
Um
and when we're talking about concerns that are b- that are, quote,
"below the threshold of criminality", unquote, that
doesn't justify imprisonment. Even if someone's, um,
not complied
with one of these orders, I don't think it's justification to, uh,
put them in prison. Something that we usually do when we need
to keep people away from the rest of society,
um,
when they haven't committed a crime.
Uh, I think it's also, uh, as some submitters have
already, uh, mentioned, it's an unjustified invasion
of privacy rights
and of the right to freedom of movement, which is
also, uh, mentioned in the regulatory impact
statement.
Um,
I think that the claim that
this sort of conduct is negatively impacting the New Zealand's
tourism industry and commercial activity more broadly is
not an evidence supported claim. And, um, I
think in the supporting doc- documentation of this bill, there is
no,
there, there's no, there's no enumerated claim of
how, what even the proposed mechanism through which this is
actually affecting income. Um,
I, I'll note that, uh, the,
the retail-
Crime report was used,
but the figure that was quoted in
the supporting documentation for this law was
the impact of retail crime broadly, and I don't think that's the
same as the impact of disorderly
conduct or
rough sleeping, which of course was not part of those figures.
I think fundamentally,
because this is a social issue,
we should be considering social responses.
And I think it's clear that the Ministry of Justice has
not considered any
way of addressing this issue that is not a justice response.
And I think that's just inappropriate
because this isn't a justice issue.
Thank you.
Fantastic. Thanks, Erin. I'll just see if members have questions.
Don't have any questions for you, Erin, but we're really grateful for your oral
submission and for being with us this evening. So thank you for your time.
Thank you.
And members, that brings us to the
Presbyterian Support Otago. Nicole.
Who's joining us online?
Nicole, if you can just accept being added as a panelist,
please.
Kia ora koutou. I'll try that for the third time. Can you hear me?
We can. We can't see you, but we can definitely hear you.
That's okay. I'm not sure what's happening with my camera, but aroha
mai. Hopefully that is keeping you awake at this
somewhat late point in the process.
And I think I've now got the camera on, so we could be looking.
Tēnā koutou. Ko Nicole Devereux toku ingoa.
Thank you for the opportunity to speak in support of Presbyterian Support
Otago's submission on the Summary Offences
Orders Amendment Bill.
We know that our submission reflects the position of feedback provided by many
others through this process, reflected even to an extent by the
last speaker.
To this end, in recognizing that it is indeed late in the day and I'm sitting
between you and a break, I will keep our oral submission brief.
As detailed in our written submission, we believe that the changes proposed in this
bill recast a societal issue presenting as
homelessness or rough sleeping as a law and order issue.
It presents a complex, nuanced problem that
requires shared responsibility and accountability,
down to one that is detailed
as an approach which can be addressed through a simple, straightforward matter of
basic safety.
Our position is that the presenting issue of homelessness, housing insecurity, and
rough sleeping should be and must be understood and responded to as a
societal and system-wide issue, not primarily as a
visibility or public order problem.
We acknowledge legitimate concerns around public safety and amenity and
however, we do not support an enforcement lead approach that risks displacing
people without addressing the housing, health, income, and
social support needs that contribute to homelessness.
Further, we believe that police already have sufficient tools at their disposal to
address the associated safety concerns when they present, which
we believe has been reflected in views expressed by others, such as the New Zealand
Police Association.
The bill may change where homelessness is visible but is unlikely to reduce
homelessness in real terms and may make it harder for people to remain
connected to support safety, whanau, community, and services.
We therefore encourage the committee to prioritize proportionate, evidence-based
support responses that address the drivers of homelessness,
strengthen safeguards against disproportionate harm, and invest in
sustainable pathways out of housing insecurity.
Attentively go here, but recognizing our place as Tangata Te
Tiriti, we also respectfully raise questions on behalf of those of us who
share responsibility for honoring Te Tiriti.
Through this change, are we responding to people in crisis as a public order
problem, or as people whose wellbeing has become disconnected from whanau,
whenua, and community? Te Tiriti o Waitangi informed
response should perhaps ask whether greater investment in housing,
kaupapa Maori services, whanau centered support, and community-based
responses could reduce the need for police intervention in the first
place. Te Tiriti o Waitangi does invite policymakers to ensure
measures that are intended to improve public safety do not
unintentionally deepen inequities for Maori or undermine the Crown's
obligations of partnership, active protection, and equitable
outcomes.
Again, we note police already have a range of powers available to respond when
there are genuine concerns about safety, disorder, intimidation, obstruction,
threatening behavior, or offending in public places.
Our concern is that the bill may create an additional enforcement pathway that is
not clearly needed and which risks being used where underlying
issues of homelessness or hardship rather than
criminal behavior.
For this reason, we ask the committee to consider whether the proposed powers are
necessary, proportionate, and supported by evidence, given the
existing tools that are already available to police, and the
risk that new powers could deepen disadvantage without improving
long-term public safety.
In Ōtepoti Dunedin, we already see both the value and limits of
support led responses. Our night shelter, Catholic social services,
community agencies, Dunedin City Council, are all trying to respond, but the
system remains stretched. The issue is not that people need more
enforcement, it is that existing housing, outreach, health, income, and
wraparound supports are not yet sufficient to meet the level of need.
Our key concern is that move on orders may displace people without
resolving the circumstances that led them to be in public
spaces in the first place. Moving someone from one location to
another may reduce visible homelessness in that place, potentially make
us feel better, but it does not provide housing, treatment,
income, safety, or connection. In practice, this can push
people into more isolated or less visible places, making it harder for
outreach workers, health providers, and community organizations such as
ours to maintain contact. It may also limit access to food
banks, social workers, libraries, healthcare, mental support,
and critically, informal community networks that are often located in
accessible public areas. We can give many examples of where this
plays out. We're also concerned that fines for non-compliance will
be ineffective and disproportionate for people experiencing homelessness or
severe hardship. For many people, fines will simply increase debt,
stress, and further contact with enforcement systems while doing nothing to
address the underlying need. We therefore urge the committee to strengthen
safeguards in the bill. At a minimum, police should be required to consider
vulnerability, disability, mental distress, age,
family harm, and housing status before issuing a move-on order.
There should also be clear guidance, monitoring, and public reporting on how these
powers are used and whether they result in connection to support.
Most importantly, any response involving a person experiencing homelessness
should, wherever practical, be accompanied by a referral to social or
appropriate support. This should sit alongside investment in
outreach, mental health, addiction, case management, income
support, culturally responsive services, and affordable and
supported housing. In closing, we encourage the committee to
measure success not by whether homelessness is moved from public view, but
by whether homelessness is reduced and people are safer, better
supported, and more connected.
Presbyterian Support Otago supports responses based on this approach.
Nga mihi nui, and thank you for your time this evening.
Thank you, Nicole, and really grateful for
your oral submission this evening and for the written submission you've done as
well. Thank you for joining us.
Ka kite.
Okay, members, we will be having a break until 8:35 when we will have our
next submitter. Thank you.
What have you got?
I might be full. Do you think, are you going to your office? We have an almighty.
What's an almighty? A God. Oh, yeah. We have God almighty.
I have.
What? You said you have an almighty.
I said, "We have God almighty."
Oh,
Tom.
Welcome back, members. We've got our next submitter, which is
Riana and Hannah, who are going to be joining us on Zoom.
Kia ora.
Hello, both. Kia ora. We can see you and hear you, which is great.
We've got you down for 10 minutes.
We have read your written submission and just leave some time at the end for
questions. Over to you.
Cool. Lovely. I'd like to start by introducing us.
I'm Riana, this is Hannah, and we are Ngā Haumi.
We've submitted before. I haven't personally,
but we're a rōpū in Kirikiriroa, working to address many
intersecting crises at this time, specifically focusing
on climate and indigenous justice.
But also so much more,
because there's so much going on. Many of us are rangatahi, some of us
are working, some of us are in school or taking care of our families.
We come to this kaupapa not from a philanthropic or
professional background, but as just human beings living alongside one
another, in a community where there are a lot of unhoused
people who have already been impacted by this bill,
and could be much further harmed by it.
So we want to-
I guess use this time to address the many horrors that have
not only happened in history but continue to be
perpetuated today, and we want to help build a future where we can all
exist in safety and in care.
So with that, I want to just make it very clear we wholly oppose this
bill.
It does not address the actual problems people face, but simply looks to
punish and further harm them. Circumstances that have led to
being unable to afford secure housing are being increased and
perpetuated by active choices by the government when it comes to job
security, food security, affordable homes, et cetera.
You can't cause the issue and then criminalize the outcome.
It doesn't make sense to be illegal to exist, especially when existing
is being made harder and harder every single day.
Ignoring the root of these issues increases things like costs of
hospital visits, arrests, imprisonment, as well as
huge amounts of health issues.
I don't know if you guys have seen this, but if you haven't,
there is a new RNZ news story about Caitlin McDonald,
called "Christchurch is My Tomb," definitely relevant to
this bill. And yeah, if you haven't seen it, definitely check it out.
Yeah. So to solve this issue by providing housing for our communities, which
is a human right,
as Malcolm Gladwell says, would be a lot easier than to manage the
consequences.
Stephanie McIntyre, who used to be the director of Downtown
Community Ministry in Wellington
said that the research shows that the mere act of placement in
housing produces a level of stabilization that allows
individuals to address their other needs more efficiently.
When asked, homeless people consistently told that they wanted to be housed.
We can't just accept that there is some group that we can't find a housing solution
for. It's not appropriate to blame the people personally for this failure,
because what's failing here is our community's ability to provide the housing
options that we all need.
I found another quote that I really liked from Michael Garza, Malachi
Garza, sorry,
and he said that the less one has, the less one has to do to get
incarcerated. This bill takes away inherent freedoms
and rights to be well and to be seen as a whole person by blaming
systemic and governmental failings on individuals.
Monique Toula from Harm Reduction Coalition said the cycle of
stigma reinforces stereotypes and labels, which in
turn reinforces stigma, which sets expectations about
roles, and these expectations lead to limited
opportunities based on what people think somebody's capable of doing.
This leads to both internalized and externalized, again, reinforced
expectations. It's a series of diminishing returns that makes it
difficult for any marginalized community to break free.
It becomes much easier to judge people instead of seeing them as human
beings who deserve love.
For many, it's easier to impose simplistic, moralistic expectations
instead of asking ourselves, what if?
What if unhoused people are people first, people who are
more than the sum total of their labor or the sum total of their ability or
appearance or their wealth.
In conclusion, this bill gives up.
It accepts that things cannot change for the better, and it admits that the
government is unwilling to put any effort into finding adequate housing or
support for unhoused people, and that's not good enough.
That's not acceptable.
There is a responsibility of the Crown government to protect and
safeguard citizens and people living here, to te tiriti, to
previously determined government targets, like addressing things like
youth mental health. This bill directly contradicts,
compromises, and undermines each of these obligations.
This bill centers and cowers to fear.
It's not based in love or in care or in life.
We,
both people and the government and everybody, need to be working
to build a better future for everyone. We cannot be afraid of each other.
We cannot be afraid of the unknown or the uncontrolled.
Our future must be based in humanity and the relationships we hold with one
another.
Thank you.
Fantastic. Thanks, Riana. And Hannah, did you want to contribute anything
just before I go to questions?
I think Riana said everything.
Fantastic. Okay, I've got a question from Carl Bates.
Thanks very much, Chair.
You made the comment that this bill accepts
that the government's not doing anything about housing,
about support, et cetera.
Can you just tell me where in the bill it says that?
Because that does not reflect my understanding of either the
bill or the huge amount of work that I've seen
firsthand that this government's done in opening new houses and
providing more social homes and opening spaces for mental health
support.
I guess I would say it doesn't explicitly say that.
That's my interpretation of it.
Ah.
But from what I can tell, and from the many
people I've talked to, and other submissions, I'm sure,
it does not seem like adequate support is being
provided because clearly there are still a lot of unhoused
people who are not getting what they need.
And maybe there is
more housing being put up, but as Hannah was saying
earlier to me, I think 40% of people within the
Waikato are food insecure at the moment, and there's just
this--
I don't know. It's
not really being addressed in the way that it needs to be and taken
as seriously as it is. And I think especially
telling people to move on
And making being on the street a criminal
offense where you can go to prison
doesn't solve anything. And there's
no faith in people who are just trying to
live their life.
Do you have any thoughts on that?
Well said.
Yeah, if I can speak to that, I think that the mere
premise that people can be moved on means that you've stopped the
buck at support.
If there's people on the streets who are at their final-
Time
... place to try and find a solution, let's say like being in a urban
center where they're able to access assistance, able to access mental
support, able to access advocate
groups, jobs, all these things. If you're moving
them out of that space simply because they create discomfort for people who are
benefiting from
many of the decisions that are being made that are bringing wealth back into a
specific group of people, and
deteriorating the wealth of community,
I think that feeds into people being unable to access
housing. And then in doing so,
you create ways in which you can push them away from those spaces where they can
access help. I don't think that means that there's support.
Yeah, Carl.
Thanks, Chair. So it's something that's come up a few times today where people are
saying that this is moving people away from support, wherein
the PR that had came out from the minister's original statement, it talks
directly to the role police have and being able to connect
people who are subject to move on orders to the right
support. Do you think people are just conveniently ignoring that
reality for political purposes?
I don't think police
being able to support people is necessarily an
adequate solution.
Connecting with the support, I think was what I said.
Yeah. I think people have a lot of
different relationships with the police.
Police have a lot of different relationships with people.
Yeah, I guess.
Can I say something?
Steve Abel.
I think-
Oh, sorry, Hannah.
Sorry, yeah. I do think that there's
been obvious solutions created
where people are directly connecting with those community
supports. I think the relationships that are built that way are much
more sustainable and are built with trust.
I think there's a lot to be done to bridge the gap between
people who
potentially have already been incarcerated or have committed
crimes that they could continue to be prosecuted for, simply for being
unable to access those community supports.
And I don't necessarily think that just by giving power to a
particular group of people instead of
empowering and creating more
safety within community spaces that people can create
trust and they're localized,
is a better solution.
Steve Abel.
Thank you, Mr. Chair.
Do you think it betrays the problem of
an economic mentality that we see manifested in this government,
whereby they've focused on the most privileged,
and the consequences of that is a great deal of marginalization
of the most vulnerable, and now they're persecuting that
group because they're uncomfortable with the fact
that people out of their desperation are now living on the streets?
Yeah, that's exactly what we're saying.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Thank you to both of you. And you made a comment,
Rhianna, earlier on about the RNZ story on
Caitlin. We actually had Caitlin's mum submit to us as the
first submitter today, Wendy,
and it was very
powerful. So if you would welcome the opportunity, it was live streamed, and you
could go back and see Wendy's extensive submission.
And I just wanted to raise that with you because you mentioned Caitlin's story as
well.
Yeah. Thank you.
Thank you
both for joining us this evening. Really appreciate your time and your submission.
Thank you.
Okay, our next submitter is Claire, who's going to be joining us in
person. Hey, Claire.
Yeah.
Come on up. Now, we've got you for five minutes.
We've read your written submission, and just leave a little bit of time at the end
for questions. Over to you.
Absolutely. Kia ora koutou.
Nō Aotearoa ahau. Nō Te Rarawa me Ngāti Wai me Ngāpuhi oku
tūpuna. Ko Claire tōku ingoa.
I'm non-binary. I use they/them pronouns.
First, I just want to say thank you all for your time this evening.
I know it's been a long day already, and it'll be a longer night going forward for
another hour or so. So really appreciate you all being here to hear from everyone.
I want to just start by saying that I'm not here on behalf of my employer,
but I will be speaking from my experience as someone who works as a housing
lawyer with people who are homeless, with people who are imminently
facing homelessness, and people who generally are in very
precarious tenancy situations. So that is my day job, and I'm coming to that with
two years of experience working in that role.
So that has really shaped my written submission, as you will have seen.
And I will just be speaking, I guess, through some points on from there, and then
will be very happy to take some questions at the end of that as well.
So,
pretty clear from my submission, I'm asking that you don't recommend that this bill
proceeds and goes any further on this.
I think that if you are persistent in moving
this forward, and that is what you are determined to do, for whatever reason you
want to,
putting it forward with removing
the inclusion of begging and rough sleeping from the bill as it stands
instead would be a better situation, though I would recommend the bill not go
forward at all.
I think that this bill does criminalize poverty.
I think there's no way of putting a shine on that.
That's just plainly the effect of having fines be issued
and prison sentences for people who are begging or rough sleeping.
We are all aware of this room. I hope that homelessness is a really big problem in
Aotearoa, one that continues to grow,
one that is very stressful, I imagine, for everyone in society, right?
No one likes to see people who are at that point in their life
where they are spending time, especially we're getting into winter, people out on
the streets. That is always going to tug on all of our heartstrings.
And I just am really shocked and upset that
the way that we are reacting to that is to criminalize that behavior,
as opposed to putting money into supports.
You might argue that we're doing both.
We're doing this end because it's important to have the carrot and the stick.
So we've got to punish people as well as put a lot of money into other options.
But I'm not seeing money getting put into those other options in a way that's
concretely changing things for the better for the people that I'm dealing with
every day.
It is really gutting to see people who are in
prison
who are only there because they didn't have an address to get bail to.
That is
really, really heartbreaking to see someone in that position.
The idea that criminalizing this might be a pathway and getting police involved is
a pathway to having this,
I guess, people get housing provided for them.
I'm really unclear on how that, I guess, works hand in hand, unless you're meaning
people are getting housing through going to prison, and then when they're getting
out, they're having really limited supports around finding housing on the other end
with those reintegration services.
So
what my submission is really putting to you is that this is trapping people in a
cycle of poverty and more incarceration.
This is from my experience firsthand working with people in this space.
I've seen how easy it is for people to slip into homelessness.
Losing your job, which a lot of people are having in the current environment,
getting behind on rent,
being unable to pay, going to the tribunal, being evicted,
going to MSD to access emergency housing and facing huge barriers there.
Especially with this newer idea about you contributing to your housing
circumstance, resulting in MSD having this wide discretion to consider
anything you could have done and said, "Hey, you actually contributed," refusing
your emergency housing grant. You'll sleep in your car that night.
It is a very easy slippery slope for so much of the population to go down.
And it's really, really gutting to see more criminalization and
more focus on punishment. I don't see how that is going
to really solve any of these problems
for anyone here.
And then I guess the final point I'd like to make before I open for questions is
just that
this bill represents a further breach of Te Tiriti o Waitangi, a
breach of the Maori right to tino rangatiratanga over kāinga.
The Waitangi Tribunal has been clear, I guess, in its interim reporting on
looking at, I guess, homelessness and that issue
from a Te Tiriti o Waitangi lens. And this represents a further breach in that
sense. And I guess final, final thing before opening for questions is just
that the time and effort spent in doing this bill and drumming all this up and all
of your time spent doing here tonight, I would much rather that time and energy and
money was spent actually funding services like Downtown Community
Ministries, like Salvation Army, like Wellington City Mission, like all these
amazing organizations that are really on the ground doing this mahi, that
are really underfunded and don't have the full supports to support this increasing
population of homelessness. I'm happy to have any questions now.
Thanks, Claire. We'll take a question from Steve Abel.
Can you see any way that this bill, if it's passed, won't result in
more people with criminal convictions and in prison who are currently
homeless?
Absolutely not. That is going to be the direct impact of this bill.
Yeah. Thank you.
Great. Thank you, Claire. Really appreciate you joining us this evening.
No, thank you for your time.
Thank you. Okay, our next submitter is Rowan, and he's going to be
joining us on Zoom.
Hey, Rowan. Thank you very much for joining us this evening.
Really appreciate you being with us.
We've read your written submission. I've got you down for five minutes.
Just please leave a little bit of time for questions at the end. Over to you.
Kia ora koutou, and thank you very much for the warm welcome.
I'm delighted to be able to talk with you this evening.
My name is Rowan McMahon. I am based in Tāmaki Makaurau,
Auckland, and I'm the director of the Auckland Street Choir.
We are a community choir that has been engaging with
the community around Central Auckland for the last 11 years.
We
are based out of Pitt Street Methodist Church, which is just off Karangahape Road,
just on Pitt Street, just literally next to the new train station.
So we have made a conscious effort with our choir to
be a very openly engaging, very
accessible choir and intentionally to reach out to
the homeless and marginalized community around the Central City.
So that's been very much our kaupapa and our jam.
So we interact daily. In fact, I've just been to our weekly practice
earlier this evening with the community that would be directly impacted by
these measures.
I'm also a former chair of the Lifewise Trust, which is a
social services trust with affiliation to the Methodist Church.
And I'm also a volunteer with the Auckland City Mission.
So I do have a little bit of interaction with the community that is directly
impacted by these measures, and I think that respectfully, I
really completely oppose them. I think they are
Not intended to, or not likely to lead to positive
outcomes for this community at all.
We're taking people who are vulnerable and putting them in
a position where they're more likely to be criminalized, and importantly, where
they're more likely to be taken away from the support services that are helping
them. So if you think of our geographic location on Pitt Street,
just off Karangahape Road, if someone has, say, a move on order for a one
kilometer radius, that would take them outside the nearby Auckland
City Mission on Hobson Street. It would also take them further past Merge Cafe on
Karangahape Road, which is two of the community facilities that would help
them. So it makes it harder for them to get support, and it makes
the life of those who are trying to reach them and trying to help them harder as
well. So, I feel that this
intention of
potentially moving people on, going well beyond existing measures
in the Summary Offences Act and other criminal
measures, and also things like trespass orders, I think it's
unnecessary, I think it's punitive, and I think it
criminalizes people who are at risk.
And
it is a growing cohort of people that unfortunately haven't quite made it onto the
bottom rung of the housing ladder. That's not their fault.
I think it would be great if we could work together for solutions that
are less punitive, involve more housing, and more help.
There are
, excuse me, lots of great charities out there like Lifewise and the Auckland City
Mission who are trying to do that, and I'm sure you've been hearing that from other
submitters as well. Thank you.
Thanks, Ron. I've got a question for you.
Just tell me a little bit about the involvement of the Auckland Street Choir
and how you engage with the homeless community.
You referenced it at the start, but I'm just keen to hear about that in a bit more
detail, please.
Yes, absolutely. Thank you. Well, the Street Choir is loosely based on
the Sydney Street Choir. I'm actually from Sydney myself.
It's an open and engaging way in which people from all walks of
life can get together and share some food, a cup of tea, and some
coffee, and the joy of singing. Now, when we sing
together or perform any kind of music, we actually get a very nice little
natural dopamine effect or an adrenaline effect which
is pleasant and encourages us to work together.
So it's a way in which we can break community barriers down.
The Street Choir performs
on a
voluntary basis for a whole range of community organizations.
We've done over 200 gigs, mostly in and around the central city.
Superb. Well, thank you for your work in that space, I appreciate it.
Now I've got a question from Steve Abel.
Thank you, Mr. Chair. Yes, music, the great healer and uniter one would hope.
You observe in your submission that it's clear that homeless people have been
pushed into their position by circumstances beyond their control, poverty,
intergenerational trauma, mental illness, addictions, and so forth.
How do you think that effective persecution through move
on orders is going to affect these people at a mental level in terms
of how they feel about their place in our society?
That's a great question. One of the reasons I think the Street Choir works as a
format is that it's a
community forum, it's not governmental, it's not the big
institutions. It's literally an open door and
manaakitanga, so it's help. It's engaging and it's open.
To put more barriers in front of people who have these barriers in front of
them all day long is going to make it even harder for them.
It's going to reduce the trust they have in government, and I think it makes their
lives harder.
Kia ora.
Fantastic. Well, thank you, Ron. Thank you so much for joining us this evening.
Really appreciate your submission.
Thank you.
Okay. We're onto our next submitter, which is
Renee, who's also going to be joining us on Zoom.
Good.
It was-
Hey, Renee, we can hear you. We can't see you at the moment.
Yeah, we're going to, um-
He's just sorting it out.
Thank you very much.
There we are.
Now I know Renee, you're going to speak for the first five minutes, and then Jeff,
you're going to speak for your submission following Renee.
Would you like us to leave questions after you speak, Renee, or after both of you
speak?
After both of us, please.
Okay, fantastic. Well, what I'll do, I'll set it for a 10 minute submission and
that'll allow time for both of you, okay?
Thank you.
Kia ora. Thank you.
Over to you.
I am Renee Hableutzl. I'm a survivor of abuse in care
after spending 16 and a half years in the Little Acre Children's Home,
overseen by then Presbyterian Social Services.
I'm here with my husband, Jeff Key, who is scheduled to speak next, and I
request that we can be heard together before questions.
We are working with Presbyterian Support Upper South Island on a project to find
survivors from the children's home and their families to ensure that
survivors have redress and support.
My foster sister almost became one of the people this bill
will criminalize. She was evicted from her home when the landlord sold
it.
She wasn't given the proper notice period, and this happened after she had been
assured that the property wasn't for sale.
The property was one of around 12 units.
The landlord took prospective buyers through the property, but claimed it was
because they couldn't access the one they were selling.
This is the sort of thing that happens to people when they are traumatized
by abuse in care and other people try to take advantage.
Thankfully, we were able to intervene with help from Presbyterian Support.
One day we were walking past someone who was begging on the street, and she said
that would be her next. I told her I would never let that happen.
I don't have the words for how angry I feel when I think
what might have happened and what this bill could have done to her.
I think about the voiceless survivors every day.
When I talk to other survivors-
They don't want to participate in any hearings like this,
because they don't believe they'll be listened to, and they don't
believe the Crown's apology was genuine.
This bill is proving them right.
Is that what you want?
I'm handing over to Jeff now.
Thank you.
Apologies for my voice. I'm recovering from a really bad dose of the
flu.
But the fact that I can barely speak, but I'm here today, tells you kind
of how much this actually matters to me.
Mostly, I'm here to support Renee.
And I got to tell you, I will be quite upset because,
and I want to just talk through that for a minute.
I was at the Crown apology in Parliament after the abuse inquiry.
I saw MPs with tears in their eyes that day from what they had
learned.
I had a genuine hope that MPs from across this
spectrum had learned from the inquiry,
and I'm upset this evening because of the things I learned through that inquiry
process have been devastating.
It also means I'm going to be quite blunt.
Renee and I are part of a process with Presbyterian Support of the South Island
to proactively find survivors from the children's home where she grew up,
to make sure that they have redress and support.
We'd love to show the committee the work we are doing,
but there's no equivalent process for state care survivors.
Through our process, as you heard, we've already secured permanent
accommodation for another survivor who was at risk of ending up on the street,
someone who would've been criminalized by this bill.
Can you imagine how upset I feel about that?
And it makes me upset and angry that we seem to be doing the complete
opposite
in Parliament to what we're doing with Presbyterian
Support. You all have the commission's reports.
You must know about the lifetime impact of abuse in care.
People are on the streets or in precarious accommodation
because the state awfully failed in a basic duty to
citizens in its care.
The state has a responsibility to find those people who abused and
ensure that they have the support that they need.
So what we should be doing is finding survivors,
providing housing, and not do this bill.
You are a justice committee. You are better than this bill,
and we will as you, please come and see our work.
Thank you, Jeff. Thank you, Renee.
Now we've got a question from Steve Abel.
Yeah. Thank you, Jeff and Renee, and for your bravery and the
important work you do, and been willing to come before the committee,
and share your personal experience, which I'm sure we all value, whatever
we think of
your position on the bill.
One of the things that came out of the abuse in state care, in talking to
survivors, was that
I spoke to a number who emphatically said there was still abuse going on
in state care, and they were most concerned that it was acknowledged that it was an
ongoing problem, that it wasn't only a historic problem.
So is it conceivable that there are people living on the streets right now,
young people and older people, who have only recently
themselves escaped abuse in state care that is
contemporaneous, and now the state is going to further
persecute them through these move on orders.
How unjust is that in your perspective?
It's outrageous. It's so inhumane.
Jeff is a better talker than me. I can hardly talk about this stuff.
It is also completely counterproductive.
Yeah.
Here are people who have been traumatized who need some support to get back on
their feet.
Mm.
Who need society to actually step up and show some responsibility.
The thing that really has stood out through this whole process,
the Royal Commission process, was time after time,
society failed to step up, not just the Crown agencies, not just government
officials, but witnesses, all manner of people didn't
step up.
And what that does to people is it just traps them.
It traps them in a world where they cannot trust.
It traps them in a world where they become more vulnerable.
They're more likely to be lost in the justice system.
They're more likely to be the people that you'll visit as
MPs with dealing with casework,
because they're the people that will have problems time and time again.
So, this is just going to make it worse. It's not going to make it better.
Mm-hmm.
Thank you. We've got a question from Camilla Belich.
Thank you both, for your powerful submission and we can see
how courageous you both are for speaking to us about these issues, and I
know they are difficult. But you said that one of the things that
was really important to you was that
politicians would listen to what you were saying, what you're
suggesting, and I just wanted to know, what is the one thing that you would
like us to take away from your submission today in terms of
something to focus on for us, to stop this
cycle that you've reflected in your submission that's been so painful?
Don't make criminals out of us.
We were treated like criminals, and all we were, were vulnerable children.
We were told we were liars, cheats, and thieves from when we were
young enough to even talk. And that's the
life that many of us have had, and we've had to fight to have
different lives. And many of us just haven't been able to make it, and,
yeah. To me, this is like watching a
horror movie, watching this play out.
The idea that my sister could have been on the street, and if I hadn't have been
able to help her Nobody was stepping up to help her.
No one was stepping up to help this woman who's never caused any harm to
anyone, ever. Never been in any trouble, ever. Yeah.
And I guess for me, the thing is whoever is
running the government after the election, you've got a really big job to do.
You know, you want
200 survivors, not counting those that are coming through the system now,
and they need to be found.
They absolutely need to be found. The process that we are doing with Presbyrian
Support, the government also needs to do.
And once that's done, you need to find what the help is that people
need and give it. Because otherwise, these problems will just keep coming back and
coming back, and we'll see bills like this that paper over the cracks and make
things worse. We actually have to invest, and it's going to cost,
but we actually have to invest the time and the money to actually find
people and get them the help that they need.
Mm.
Fantastic. Well, thank you Renee, and thank you Jeff, and can I just say what a
formidable team you make together.
So thank you both for being with us this evening and for submitting on this
legislation. So thank you very much.
Thank you for your time.
Thank you.
Fantastic. Okay, our next submitter is Helen and Francine, who are
also going to be joining us on Zoom.
Hi there.
Hi Helen. How are you?
Good, thank you.
Is Francine
online there?
Yes, she is. Yes.
Oh.
We're just going to get her... We can see you, Helen.
So what we'll do, we'll start your submission. There she is. She's joined us now.
Yeah.
We've got you for five minutes. We've read your written submission.
Just leave a little bit of time at the end for questions. Over to you.
Oh, Francine.
Francine has got it written down for us.
Is she able to read it out?
Yes, absolutely. She'll just need to unmute herself, please.
Okay.
Francine, have you unmuted yourself?
Sorry.
It's a work in progress. There we go.
There she is.
Thank you. I thought I was going to be just as a support
person in the background, but thank you, Helen.
Thank you, committee.
Helen and I,
we live in Kapiti, and I have been doing some
voluntary work for an organization. I won't name it.
But we have been working with and coming across
homeless people up in the Waikanae area.
And we've seen an
increase in this happening across Kapiti, and in particular
where we're living in the Waikanae area.
Mm.
What I'd like to do is to actually say that
while we believe in
a fundamental right for the general public and business people is to
feel safe and to be able to go about their lives as they wish,
but this also extends to people who are homeless or who are
sleeping rough and on our streets, in
doorways of shops. There is no dignity for anyone
who is homeless and vulnerable and lacking safe shelter
and being isolated from their community.
So we're opposing the moving on orders, but would rather
the bill, we would like it to be withdrawn, and we would like a
more humane and dignity to all approach be taken
by the government and communities for all those who are homeless.
This national discussion has highlighted the plight of those
who are homeless, and it provides an opportunity for us now
to find appropriate housing and social support
services for all people.
As I said,
Kapiti District Council, social service organizations,
and members of the
communities
are seeing an increase in people who are
experiencing homelessness, who are sleeping rough.
And so what we've been finding is that it's
not only the people who we are actually finding
sleeping on grass verges outside the train
stations,
hiding in shop corners.
It's also people who are sleeping rough, and by that I
mean women and children who
are sleeping with other families-
Yeah
... as well. And I think there's also,
from what I understand and from the conversations I have with
people, these people also end up on the street.
And so they're not criminals. We should not be criminalizing them.
They're people that need homes and support
services. There's very limited
alternative housing in Kapiti. We do have some boarding
houses, transitional and social housing, and
holiday parks. But it's not enough.
And so people are forced to live
roughly.
What we find is that
each person's different. They have a story to tell about
their life.
Some have more internal resources than others.
Some might be transient, and they may need food and
clothing, but they do want to move on.
But to do it in a way that they're in charge of that, not to have
the police enforce that.
Yeah.
Other people need much more s-
Material support. And so often we link,
um, we link people with organizations, um, who can,
who can better assist.
We often find that there are people, um, with very complex needs,
uh, they, they have maybe mental health needs, addiction
issues, um, maybe some, uh, antisocial or what's
perceived as antisocial behavior.
They also have a high level of distrust in any government
agency, any hospital, and social services.
And the conversations that I have with people is that it's
because of the history of abuse in state care,
um, that this is of- this often happens.
Yeah.
People, people are often illiterate, um, they may have spent
time in prison, and so they have far less social skills than,
than others in our community.
And what we find is building trust with people takes
time and effort, and, uh, so
a, a very short, sharp solution of moving someone on
is not even taking the time to listen and to build
trust in what's been happening for them and how we might
actually be able to help. It's also very difficult for
people to access GPs. So, um,
and there are barriers to that around
just enrolling in a PHO or a GP practice.
Also, there are long wait lists for doctors as well up in this
area. Uh.
I'll just get you to make some closing remarks, if that's all right.
I will, yeah.
As we have met our time.
Thank you. I think one of, what a- what we'd like to see
is a, a human dignity approach, um,
taken for people who are in this situation.
And what I mean by that is some of the things that I've talked about.
I also think that we have, um, we also
need a multilevel approach to s- uh, for people
who need safe shelter, uh, inappropriate housing.
I think
what's, what I find happening is we've got a lot of emphasis on tradition,
uh, on building new houses, which is great, but there
are some people who cannot live as we would live.
And what they lack is hygiene, you know, things like
showers and laundry.
Mm.
And a place to s- a safe place to stay.
So I'd like to see the government look at that part of, uh, um,
of housing.
Sh-
Yeah. Night shelters or place where they can go and eat,
have a shower, have a kōrero, have some kai, and,
um, feel very comfortable in that environment, but not necessarily being put
into homes as such that we consider
the right-
Fantastic. Well, I need to stop you both there and say thank you so much for
your submission this evening, and also for the written submission you've made on
the bill, and we appreciate you joining us. So thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Thank you. Okay, members, next submitter is Scott, who's also going to be joining
us on Zoom.
Mm-hmm.
Bye.
Good. Uh, kia ora koutou. Um,
can you see me at the moment? I'm just-
We can't, Scott, but we can hear you. Uh, if you just turn your camera on.
There we go.
Oh, yeah. Thank you.
Fantastic. Uh, we've got you for five minutes, and we've read your written
submission, so over to you.
Uh, yeah. Thanks very much. Uh, tena koutou katoa.
Ngā mihi nui kia koutou. Um, pomare, everyone.
Um, thanks for this chance to talk to the select committee.
I'm just speaking as a recently retired public health physician of
40 years. Um,
um, so I'm guessing
the key things I was wanting to say are pretty much written in this,
uh, in the written submission, but in effect,
nobody wakes up or as a child dreams of
becoming homeless or dreams of sleeping rough.
And I wanted to make the point that I'm currently,
uh, I guess,
not homeless, but you never know at what stage people can
become vulnerable in their lives, either yourselves or
maybe family members, your kids, or siblings, or
whatever. We're all vulnerable at some stage in life, uh, certainly when we're
born.
Ideally, when we die, we will have somebody beside us,
but it's a bit chilling looking at some of the epidemiology around
this. So, um, I just want to sort of really spend the rest of the
time just highlighting some material that you'll already be aware of.
Uh, was a, um, analysis of coronial
inquests, um, between 2008 and
2019 in New Zealand, about 171
cases of people who have no fixed abode.
And I just kind of thought it's really interesting to read through that and just to
kind of imagine what it's like. So the data was saying something
like the average age of death of, of people of no
fixed abode was something like, um, 46
years. So that was a loss of something like 30 years life
expectancy on average. Um,
majority were, um, underlying causes, something like
42% were due to, um, cardiovascular
disease or other kind of natural type causes.
Um, three cases were death by hypothermia, the
cold.
Um, clear suicide with good of evidence, something, was something
like a third of cases.
Mm.
Um,
and then you had accidental deaths as well happening.
and I guess the other thing was the location of deaths.
Most commonplace where death occurred, regardless of the cause of death, was in
public spaces such as streets, doorways, parks and reserves, forests,
beaches, harbors or rivers,
followed by private cars or campervans
I guess that speaks to me, I guess, of the loneliness of what is an
invisible population. So, people like this don't get
obituaries in the newspaper. It's pretty much
below the surface.
And in many ways, this bill is just trying to
replicate that and make that worse.
So, the move-ons is just trying to exacerbate a problem
there, moving them out of the way a wee bit like people were moved out of
the way, or the
streets
where removed the beggars at various Olympic Games.
So, I guess that's my main point, just to sort of keep in mind
people don't choose to become homeless, to
sleep rough, and criminalizing it is not going to help anybody.
That's me.
Fantastic. Thanks, Scott. We've got a question from Steve Abe.
Yeah, those are profound and powerful figures, Scott.
You interestingly in your submission quoted the Bible, "The poor will always be
with us", and pointed out that that alludes to a point
of us needing to have some sort of limitless generosity in regards to
homelessness. But I wonder, how does it reflect on us as a
society that such a bill as this that
vilifies
the human dignity of those most desperate in our
society or most vulnerable, how does it reflect on us more broadly?
Not well.
I just think it's
a shame. It's disappointing. I read the minister's
comments, which were all directed about the well-being of business
owners, and that's important. But it's this invisible
population that we are
kind of throwing under the bus that really upsets me.
I think as a society,
the tenor of a
society is how it treats its most vulnerable members.
And in our case, it's not
a good look. It's a very bad look.
Got it.
Fantastic. Well, thank you very much, Scott.
Really appreciate your time this evening and for joining us. So, thank you.
Thank you.
Okay, our next submitter is Johnny, who's going to be joining us in person, and
he's been waiting very patiently.
In your hands, Johnny.
Thank you.
Namaste. Hello. Ko Johnny tōku
ingoa. My name is Johnny Apavinnak.
I come here as an individual with the knowing
that I'm only here because you are here,
and I'm thankful for that.
We are totally interdependent for our existence, our survival,
and ultimately for our flourishing.
I have worked with disadvantaged youth for the past 15 years, and the last
almost two years I've worked with homeless and street whanau at the Wellington
City Mission.
I'm here today as someone who sees the inherent good in all people,
and plead with you members of the committee to take a humanized
approach
when deliberating over the issue and not render it
to an issue of economics.
I will now share with you a song I wrote that expresses my gratitude and
support
for our most vulnerable members of society.
Say there must be some way to live within a rough
town. Oh, there must be some peace within the
city.
Say there must be some way to live within a rough
town. Oh, there must be some peace within the
city.
Pollution in the air. Confusion and
despair. Collusion of the highest order within
the public sphere. Assumption choice by fear.
Seeking a figurehead to steer. Out of control in a sensory
life, exhausted, too much to care.
Oh,
when will you see with the
eyes you've been blessed
with,
that you are just like me.
Say there must be some way to live within a rough
town. Oh, there must be some peace within the city.
town. Must be some peace within the
city.
Like the book says, the kingdom is
inside. So why do we veer to the highest heights but neglect
the peace of mind. In the business of
surviving a capitalist life. Must hold onto our
humanity, for they wish to quantify.
Order, order. We must maintain the order.
Where the people sleep is apparently a travesty for
decorum. Scat along, get along, move along, get a job, get up
on down the road. Hold the sight out the mind, oh, there's no
problem to behold. Scat along, get along, move along, get
a job, get up on down the road. To sweep it under the
carpet without carrying the load.
Scat along, get along, move along, get a job, get up on down the road.
Divert the water flowing, ends up sinking our whole
boat. Scat along, get along, move along, get a job, get up on
down the road. It's the hideout of society, and it
leads us to implode. Well, there must be some way to
live within a rough town. Oh, there must be some
peace within the city.
Say there must be some way to live within a rough
town. Oh, there must be some peace within the city.
But they tell them move on.
But they
tell
them move on.
But they tell them move on. They tell them move on. But they tell them move on.
He aha te mea nui o te ao?
What is the most important thing in our world?
He tangata, he tangata, he tangata.
It's the people, it's the people, it's the people.
Thank you.
Phenomenal, Johnny.
Phenomenal.
Absolutely phenomenal. Well done, mate.
And
thank you for your courage to come before us this evening,
and very well written. But thank you very much.
Just want to commend you for that, so thank you.
Thank you for your time.
Thanks, Johnny. Thank you.
Mr. Chair, can I request if,
Johnny, you could give us the lyrics to your fantastic song?
Yeah, absolutely.
If you've got them written down.
Yeah.
That'd be awesome.
Steve would also like copyright.
No.
As long as he doesn't sing it, we'll be okay.
Yes, absolutely, Johnny. Yep.
It's good to go.
More than happy for you to send that through, so thank you very much.
Thanks a lot, comment. Cheers.
Thanks for joining us.
Thank you, mate.
Okay,
our next submitter is Lex, who's going to be joining us on Zoom.
Kia ora.
Hi, Lex. Thank you very much for joining us this evening.
We've got you down for five minutes. We've read your written submission.
Just leave some time for questions at the end. Over to you.
Thank you.
Kia ora, my name's Lex. I'm just going to be expanding on my written
submission.
First of all, I want to talk about how
this bill
is really just criminalizing homelessness and poverty,
and it's going to have very negative impacts
for our houseless communities, and also
for
... Oh, sorry.
Yeah, because this bill kind of defines things that
can constitute an order to move on as very
vague and sort of unavoidable symptoms of poverty
and being houseless,
like rough sleeping and indicating an intent to inhabit a
public space.
And it's sort of adding a lot of power to police that
is not necessary. It doesn't provide a benefit.
And it really just poses a danger to the most vulnerable
groups in our society because
they don't have any other choice but to sleep on the streets or
to be where they are.
Because it's often the
safest place to be is in a public setting where there
are eyes on you to make sure that nothing bad's going to
happen. And giving police the
power to
move people on is really just moving people out of
sight, but it's not actually addressing the root of the issue.
And
yeah, it can force vulnerable people into more unsafe
areas,
and
just for
sort of the benefit of having a bit more comfort,
which really shouldn't outweigh the safety and
well-being of our most vulnerable members of
society.
Because
there's not really, even for business owners,
police already have powers to
disrupt behavior that is genuinely causing an issue.
And by giving them this extra power,
it's kind of hard to regulate because it's very much a
there when you're in the moment
law that there's not a lot of oversight for it,
and so it can lead to a lot of problems.
And
yeah, ultimately,
someone trying to sleep in a place that is most safe for them
isn't going to cause a major issue.
And even at its absolute best case, if you
did argue that there's a slight benefit to businesses, maybe they get
a
few more people coming through because there isn't someone sleeping outside.
Ultimately, that slight benefit isn't
enough to outweigh the harm that's going to be caused
to our houseless whanau, to relationships between
homeless folks and police, and because it's going to create a lot of
negativity
and bad
opinions towards police, which is just going to make everything a lot worse.
And so, yeah, ultimately, I
strongly oppose this bill because it poses no significant
benefit. It does not improve safety
because laws are already in place about safety and
actual problematic behavior. This is really just criminalizing poverty.
So,
are there any questions?
Fantastic. We've got a question from Steve Abel, Lex.
Yeah, thank you very much, Lex.
Do you similarly reflect to me that it feels as if it's, and you alluded to
this earlier on in your submission,
the discomfort
that is felt by the presence of homeless people
is most simplistically solved by simply getting them
out of sight and therefore out of mind, rather than actually
properly addressing the causes of that homelessness and actually helping those
people
where help is clearly needed?
Exactly.
Yeah, I think that's the thing. It's not addressing the root of the issue.
It's just sweeping it under the rug to try and make people feel more
comfortable, but it's not making anyone's life actually better.
Yeah. In fact, it makes people's lives worse.
Yeah.
Thank you, Lex. Really appreciate you joining us this evening, and for your written
submission as well. So thank you for your time.
Thank you.
Okay.
Excuse my pronunciation, but Prayash.
Yeah, that's me.
Come on up. Thank you very much.
Yes.
Thank you for joining us. We've read your written submission, and we've got you for
five minutes. Over to you.
Kia ora. Mā tuatahi, tēnei te mihi ki ngā mana whenua o tēnei takiwā.
Ā, ko Taranaki whānau ki te opuku o te ika me Ngāti Tūrangatira hoki.
Tēnei ko te tena koutou, tena koutou, tena koutou katoa.
Ā, tua toru-- tua rua, tēnei te mihi i tēnei whare, te whare o
kāwanatanga. Tēnei koe, tua toru.
Tēnei te mihi ki ngā rangatira
mō te Justice Committee me ngā kaiwhakahaere i
muri katoa. Tēnei koutou, tena koutou katoa.
Ko wai ahau? Ko tangata Tiriti, a mō te global majority.
He uri ahau mō Nepal.
Ko Prayash toku ingoa. First of all, I would like to acknowledge the mana whenua of
this takiwā, this region where we are gathered here today for my presenting
submissions. Taranaki whānau,
ki te opuku o te ika me Ngāti Tūrangatira.
Obviously, I also want to acknowledge all the leaders
who are here, as well as our managers behind the scenes.
My name is Prayash. I'm a tangata Tiriti from the global majority, and I whakapapa
to Nepal. And today, I am here to use my voice, and thank you for
allowing me to use this space and platform.
But before I start, I also want to acknowledge
my voice and platform to express in solidarity with every rangatahi,
every youth, and every Gen Z who are out there in India, especially in Delhi,
expressing their rights, their basic rights, and demanding the right questions to
the state and authorities in India, especially in Delhi, as I
said, for the cockroach on the party moment that's happening currently, and it's
quite disturbing to see what's happened yesterday.
So I'm here far away from my whenua, but I hear you, I listen to you,
and I'm in solidarity with all of the rangatahi, the future of India.
Now, coming back to this bill. I strongly oppose this bill for many reasons.
But primarily when I was looking at those insertions 8A to 8H,
I see that it refers to offense so many times, and it talks about the
additional power
providing to the police. And
there are many ways the police already have so much of mechanism and power in
place to tackle those offenses. And
anyone living in the street and anyone living in unhoused or building
anything is not by a choice. It's a systematic failure.
It's a collective failure of our society.
So I do not see this bill addressing any of those issues, the core
fundamental issues that we have in our society.
And in that way, I also do not believe in handing an extra
power which do not address any of those issues.
And also, where will they move on? Will they move on from Cuba Street to
Parramatta? Will they move on from where? Where to go?
So instead, I believe in handing over more additional power to the community.
And when this bill was been pushed to the
community or this amendment came out, were they even been consulted?
When I say, "Were they been given consulted?" I meant by the Wellington
city missions or those hapori or those community or the collective or the
organizing who've been working day in, day out with those
community who are already marginalized by our society, by our
collective failure, by our systematic failure.
And I would also say the institutional failure and the policies that we have in
place. So
having said that,
when I was looking at the media briefing by the Minister of 14th May 2026,
there was a big rhetoric in the media about the reclaiming our streets and
making this space safe for everybody who comes to work in this
urban space, and that's such a privileged statement to talk about.
I think this whenua is for everybody, and when I say everybody, especially it is
more for the marginalized community who have already been discriminated by the
society, by us. And when I say by us, I also meant by me.
What am I doing here? So I'm standing in solidarity with all those whānau who have
been living hard life in the streets.
So we do not want to dehumanize them.
All we want to do is to share our aroha and manaakitanga or
whatever we want to do that with our own privilege that we have there.
And also thinking about the intersectionality of the whānau that kind of creates a
bigger impact and which is not even included in this
particular address, in this particular bill.
When I say intersectionality of the whānau, the rangatahi whānau, how can we even
propose a bill which can criminalize a rangatahi of 14 years old?
How? Is that a society that we want to build on?
As I said earlier, that there are already a mechanism that police have so much
power. Instead, what I would like to, as my closing statement, is that
there are two closing statement I would like to make, that we have to move on from
this bill. We don't want this bill in our society, as in Aotearoa at all.
The bill doesn't have any place
when there is already a mechanism.
And the second point that I want to make is that we have to create a more space
where-- when I say more space, more community and safe space within that all
this whānau who are living in the margin of our society can move in
instead. So that's how I would like to end my-- So instead of moving
probably, I would say move into this space. Yeah.
Kia ora koutou.
Kia ora. Well, fantastic. Thank you so much for joining us this evening, and
appreciate you submitting to us and being here this late as well.
So thank you.
Kia ora.
Members, our next submitter isn't here in person, so we're going to move to
Visionwest Community Trust, who is joining us online. So.
Gidday, Jeremy. Thank you very much for joining us.
We have read your written submission. We've got you down for 10 minutes.
Please do just leave a little bit of time for questions at the end.
But over to you and Judy
Great. Kia ora koutou. Ko Jeremy toku ingoa.
I'm representing Visionwest,
and I am the Supportive Housing Outreach Team
Leader at Visionwest, who provides
housing first, transitional housing, and so forth,
mainly in West Auckland, but also down in Christchurch as well.
For outreach, we cover both West Auckland and the North Shore.
For me personally, I have been working with those experiencing homelessness
for around 30 years, and 25 of those
years were in Chicago, and I came back to Tāmaki
five years ago.
In my various roles, I have played a part in helping,
sometimes small, sometimes big, and helping hundreds if not thousands of
individuals and families find housing.
And I can undoubtedly say that punitive
measures have not only caused homelessness, but it
also prolongs homelessness.
When people get moved around, fined, or jailed, it
disrupts
our flow as workers, and it creates massive barriers.
And when I say that it disrupts us,
I want us to take into
account the tāngata that we work with and how much more painful it
is for them, and the disruption of their lives.
I want to just speak on three things from my experience, is
how moving people
can put people more at risk. I heard earlier about the
life expectancy difference
of 20 or 30 years, as well as people who are
homeless are more likely to be victims of
crime and all that. And when we move people from one
location to another, it
puts them more at risk with their health and so forth, and
more likely to be victims and so forth because especially our most
vulnerable, our wāhine,
those who are immunocompromised, the elderly,
those in the rainbow community.
Recently, there's been a few people that have been-- The second point I want
to bring up is trust and distrust.
Our outreach team is a team of eight people that go about,
and we get referrals every day of rough sleepers all
over West Auckland and North Shore.
And when people get moved,
part of our role is to build trust,
and that when people are being told to move,
that trust is lost, and it really affects their
wairua and
so forth. And so sometimes we have to start again.
And that's why I say it often prolongs homelessness,
which is my third point. Because
when people get moved, we have to try and find them again.
Even recently, even this past week when someone
was moved
recently,
they had a housing appointment, and it just
disrupted that way, and we had to
find them again and go into different areas, and we couldn't find them, so they
missed their housing appointment, and sometimes there's a short timeframe in that.
And then fines will increase debt and so forth.
So,
that is quite a struggle for our team sometimes,
and I can't imagine how painful it is
for those who are sleeping rough.
Visionwest's main values are aroha,
manaakitanga, and whanaungatanga, and mana.
And I believe that we as a society should follow that
and uplift people and uplift their mana and so forth rather
than
looking at punitive measures.
I think we should put more time, effort, and money into solutions that are
healthier, safer, and would be more cost-effective,
such as supportive housing with wraparound services,
immediate access housing and so forth, where we can come around and
support people. I want to end my part of
this talk with
a cautionary tale. It comes from Chicago, in memory of a rough
sleeper I knew named Nick.
Nick couldn't read or write. He was extremely
immunocompromised. He had no known family.
He didn't have any IDs, and we were working extensively with him.
And when he was told to move on in
this particular incident,
he was very frustrated, and because he was
neurodivergent and so forth, he was yelling at the people.
I was there and witnessed all this.
Because he couldn't understand what was happening. He didn't threaten anybody.
He just yelled, and he used some swear words and so forth.
When he moved, we couldn't find him
because we were helping him with his diet and everything like that.
And several months later,
or not even several months later, he was found passed away under a
tree, which was very tragic to us.
And I live with that memory personally myself,
because I knew this guy and how much effort we'd put into him,
and getting him to move on was a--
That's why I lift up his name even 22 years later because of
that, and that's where I see the danger of the
move-on orders. I will hand it over to
Judy now.
Tēnā koutou katoa. Talofa lava. Mālō e lelei.
My name is Judy
Mataia. I'm the Director of Housing and Pasifika Development at
Visionwest.
It also incorporates work that we're doing in the counties
Manukau area and Auckland. I'm really just here
to tautoko
the insight that Jeremy shared. A lot of it is already in the submission,
which I take it has been read by the committee.
And really, the Visionwest
position is to recommend to the committee that it
withdraws the support for the bill.
And so many people have mentioned
this in their whakaaro before us. And how amazing was that
dude and his song? If me and Jeremy got ourselves together, we would've
come up with a rap or something.
But it was really just to think about
we already have
police powers that can address antisocial
behavior, safety concerns,
aggressiveness, public nuisance.
So we've already got those in place.
What I think the orders do specifically for our
homeless and rough sleepers is that it just
targets them specifically. It feels like it targets
them.
And the presence of the people who are experiencing
homelessness or rough sleeping
is more evidence that our housing system
is fractured, our welfare system is broken.
It doesn't point to a high-functioning
community when we think about the ways that we should hold those
who are most vulnerable, and those who have the least voice,
those who have the least resource, who have the
least power. This is the way we want to treat those of
our community? So really it's just thinking about what
is working really well in Aotearoa.
How do we
activate more support services? And the government have
done great work so far in supporting Housing First as
an initiative. But they could do more to really
mobilize the work that Jeremy's team does.
And so many of the other outreach teams in Tāmaki and
Ōtautahi.
People have mentioned Lifewise, Auckland City Mission,
Salvation Army. Jeremy and the team work
together with each of those services.
It really is a collaborative approach, and I would just really hope that the
committee hears that we've got some things that are working.
Why would we vilify those in our community that
have the least?
And so that's really the position that we're taking from
Visionwest.
Fantastic. We've got a question from Steve Abel.
Thank you very much, Mr. Chair.
And greetings from Waitākere.
That's my neck of the woods.
How demoralizing is it for you, given the
vitally important and hard work that you put in to help
homeless people and protect homeless people, that
this legislation will now be, in a sense, pitting you
against the police as well? Because the effect of the move on orders
will be to harm the efforts that you're making
and even undermine your work. And how
unhelpful and demoralizing is that?
Yes, it can be very
demoralizing. But at the same time,
there's been a lot of community work that we have done,
in that we can get referrals from there from
the local boards and from the police sometimes.
And so we can hopefully
go before the police move them on. But yes, it can
be demoralizing, especially when you work hard with
somebody and we
don't know where they're at. And of course, it's more demoralizing on
the individuals, especially if they have to move out of somewhere and go into
another place. But
thankfully, we've had a couple of referrals from the police recently, so we can go
down there before they actually do move people on.
So that has been an encouragement.
But yes, I have definitely saw it in Chicago when people moved on, and
it
can pit you against other
government agencies like the police.
So I definitely saw that in Chicago, and it is demoralizing and very hard
to try and deal with that.
Thank you.
Great. Well, thank you very much, Jeremy and Judy.
Appreciate both of you joining us this evening, and thank you for your time.
Thank you.
Thank you for letting us share.
Okay, we've come to our last submitter, which is Catherine, who's going to be
joining us on Zoom as well.
Hey, Catherine. Thank you very much for joining us this evening.
We've got you down for five minutes. We've read your written submission.
We'll just leave a little bit of time at the end for questions. But over to you.
Thank you so much, and good evening.
So firstly, I would like to thank all the members of the committee for their
time listening to the submissions before mine, mine and those that
will come after. I understand you guys have had a rather long day.
I come to you from my warm, dry home, something I
and my family are very fortunate to have.
But sadly, in New Zealand, housing is a privilege rather than a
right.
But housing should be a basic human right.
But those in power, time and time again
Mainly the government and landlords have the right to dictate who does and
does not deserve a home, a place of safety, place of
sanctuary.
Homelessness and begging is a result of the failure of adequate
housing and a failure to ensure people can meet their most basic
human needs. These two things being included
in this amendment is deeply concerning.
This will only further isolate and risk the safety of these people, push them
into other areas where they will continue to be unwanted,
pushed out of view, including to prison if they refuse to and
cannot pay a substantial fine.
Three months, or in reality under current law six weeks in prison,
will achieve what exactly? The loss of the few belongings they may have,
the ability to maybe not be able to improve their situation,
gain employment, maybe find a house because they now have a criminal conviction
for essentially being poor.
Ultimately, who's that serving? Who is that benefiting?
I believe that this proposal is cruel, it's inhumane.
It says, "We don't care. We don't want you.
You don't deserve to be part of our community.
We'd rather you be out of sight so that tourists and other members of the community
don't have to see you."
Homeless people, people on the streets, are members of our community.
They are part of our society, and they do belong.
They need compassion, not punishment and further isolation.
Now I ask everyone listening to me, think about this.
How would you feel if you're already marginalized, at a low point in your
life, rejected, ignored, walked past, treated
like a piece of rubbish on the footpath,
to then be told to go away? "We don't want to see you here."
Further to this, think about a child, 14, 15,
16, 17, someone who should have a warm, safe home,
maybe with their parents or someone that they trust.
They're told to go away. They may end up entering the criminal justice
system,
a cycle that's actually really hard to break.
This could be your child, your niece and nephew, a friend's child.
What would you do? How would you feel?
Is this how we wish to treat children or anyone for that matter?
As you all go home tonight, or to your
accommodation, into a warm bed and a place of
safety, imagine yourself as someone with nowhere to go,
no sense of safety. Not knowing if you'll be attacked tomorrow,
eat anything, if someone will show you kindness, treat you as a human,
or simply walk on by.
We cannot know one's journey unless we have walked in their shoes.
We cannot understand that feeling if we've never experienced it.
I'm imploring MPs, the people we place trust in to protect and serve our
society, to reject this bill. Please listen to the experts,
government departments who have voiced a concern, and well, everyday
Kiwis like me saying this is wrong.
It's not really who New Zealand is, and I don't think this is something that we as
a nation want to be known for. Thank you for listening.
Thank you, Catherine. There we go.
We've got a question from Steve Abel.
Thank you, Mr. Chair, and thank you, Catherine.
I wonder, you articulate, I think very powerfully,
a principle of compassion that we should
embody as a society,
because we exactly do not know what the life experience
is of another person. So when we see somebody in a state of
hardship, such as homelessness, we should bring to
them
our shared humanity and show them compassion, and this
bill does the opposite of that, doesn't it?
Yes, absolutely.
Thank you.
Fantastic. Thank you, Catherine.
Really appreciate you submitting with us so late in the evening.
So thank you very much for your time-
Yeah, no problem
... and your submission. Thank you.
Thank you. Have a great night, everyone. Bye-bye.
Thank you.
I thank our members in the gallery who've joined us this evening.
Thank you for staying so late. To those of you that submitted today and
those that didn't, thank you very much. Now I just need to ask you to leave.
Thank you.
No, I just have to look at that painting before I leave.